<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25749501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4352038</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120413</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-44876</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intermittent Fasting Results in Tissue-Specific Changes in Bioenergetics and Redox State</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Redox and Bioenergetic Effects of Intermittent Fasting</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chausse</surname><given-names>Bruno</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vieira-Lara</surname><given-names>Marcel A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>Ang&#x000e9;lica B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>Marisa H. G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kowaltowski</surname><given-names>Alicia J.</given-names></name><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Departamento de Bioqu&#x000ed;mica, Instituto de Qu&#x000ed;mica, Universidade de S&#x000e3;o Paulo, S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gueven</surname><given-names>Nuri</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Tasmania, AUSTRALIA</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BC MAVL ABS MHGM AJK. Performed the experiments: BC MAVL ABS. Analyzed the data: BC MAVL ABS MHGM AJK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MHGM AJK. Wrote the paper: BC MAVL ABS MHGM AJK.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>alicia@iq.usp.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e0120413</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chausse et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0120413.pdf"/><abstract><p>Intermittent fasting (IF) is a dietary intervention often used as an alternative to caloric restriction (CR) and characterized by 24 hour cycles alternating <italic>ad libitum</italic> feeding and fasting. Although the consequences of CR are well studied, the effects of IF on redox status are not. Here, we address the effects of IF on redox state markers in different tissues in order to uncover how changes in feeding frequency alter redox balance in rats. IF rats displayed lower body mass due to decreased energy conversion efficiency. Livers in IF rats presented increased mitochondrial respiratory capacity and enhanced levels of protein carbonyls. Surprisingly, IF animals also presented an increase in oxidative damage in the brain that was not related to changes in mitochondrial bioenergetics. Conversely, IF promoted a substantial protection against oxidative damage in the heart. No difference in mitochondrial bioenergetics or redox homeostasis was observed in skeletal muscles of IF animals. Overall, IF affects redox balance in a tissue-specific manner, leading to redox imbalance in the liver and brain and protection against oxidative damage in the heart.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo &#x000e0; Pesquisa do Estado de S&#x000e3;o Paulo (FAPESP), grant 10/51906, Instituto Nacional de Ci&#x000ea;ncia e Tecnologia de Processos Redox em Biomedicina (INCT Redoxoma), N&#x000fa;cleo de Apoio &#x000e0; Pesquisa Redoxoma (NAP Redoxoma), Centro de Pesquisa, Inova&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o e Difus&#x000e3;o de Processos Redox em Biomedicina (CEPID Redoxoma) grant 13/07937-8, and the John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation. MAVL (grant 13/14203-0) is supported by an undergraduate fellowship from FAPESP. BC is supported by a CNPq fellowship. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Moderate reduction in <italic>ad libitum</italic> daily caloric intake without limiting essential and micronutrient access (caloric restriction, CR) is a well-established mechanism to promote longer lifespans and/or healthier aging in a wide range of organisms, including humans [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The beneficial effects of CR diets are complex and widespread, but include the preservation over time of mitochondrial bioenergetic functions and redox balance (the difference between the production and removal of damaging oxidative species) [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>The downside of CR is that it requires daily control of caloric intake, and is thus labor-intensive both for humans and to maintain in a laboratory animal setting. As an alternative to CR, some groups have proposed the use of intermittent fasting (IF), also referred to as intermittent feeding or every other day feeding [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], in which <italic>ad libitum</italic> feeding periods are alternated with fasting, thus avoiding the strict daily control of caloric intake. In laboratory animals, this feeding protocol was first described by Carlson and Hoelzel, who observed a slight increment in rat life span [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Despite this early result suggesting a lifespan benefit similar to CR, subsequent studies have indicated that the enhancement in life expectancy promoted by IF, if present, is certainly less robust [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In humans, IF has been shown to reduce obesity and have positive effects on some pathologies [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Despite some similarities such as promoting reduced body weight [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], substantial differences between CR and IF have been uncovered [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and are, indeed, expected, since CR involves a daily reduction in food intake, while IF changes feeding frequency, and may not always result in a limitation of food ingestion [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In fact, while CR enhances insulin sensitivity, we find that long-term IF results in insulin resistance [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. We also find that long-term IF enhances tissue oxidant release and oxidative protein modifications in the skeletal muscle and adipose tissue [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], while long-term CR is mostly associated with the prevention of oxidative damage [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Overall, IF effects on oxidative balance are not yet well determined. This study bridges this knowledge gap, and demonstrates that short-term IF affects redox balance in a tissue-selective manner.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Animals</title><p>Experiments were conducted in agreement with the NIH guidelines for the humane treatment of animals and were approved by the local Animal Care and Use Committee (Comiss&#x000e3;o de &#x000c9;tica em Cuidado e Uso Animal&#x02014;Instituto de Qu&#x000ed;mica, USP) (Permit number: 21/2014). Male, 8-week-old Sprague Dawley rats were separated in two groups: one fed <italic>ad libitum</italic> (AL), and one with <italic>ad libitum</italic> access to food on alternating days (IF). The animals were lodged four individuals per cage in 12 hours light/dark cycles and given water <italic>ad libitum</italic>. Body mass was recorded before and after 1 month of the dietary intervention and cumulative food consumption over the treatment period was recorded for each cage. The average intake per animal was used to calculate feed conversion efficiency (average weight gain per cage &#x000d7; 100/average food intake per cage). Chow was alternately placed or removed at 5:00 pm for IF animals. After 1 month of the dietary intervention, AL and IF rats were euthanized by decapitation after 12 hours of overnight fasting.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Mitochondrial isolation</title><p>Mitochondrial isolation from different tissues was performed as described by Tahara et al., 2009 [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Briefly:</p><p><bold>Liver mitochondria</bold>. The tissue was minced finely and washed with 4&#x000b0;C isolation buffer (250 mM sucrose, 10 mM Hepes, 1 mM EGTA, pH 7.2) and then homogenized with a 40 mL tissue grinder. The suspension was centrifuged at 600 g for 5 minutes and the resulting supernatant was centrifuged at 12,000 g for 5 minutes. The pellet was washed and resuspended in a minimal volume of the same buffer.</p><p><bold>Brain mitochondria</bold>. The preparation used digitonin to release mitochondria from synaptosomes, resulting in a mixture of synaptosomal and nonsynaptosomal mitochondria. The brain was minced and washed with 125 mM sucrose, mannitol 250 mM, 10 mM Hepes, 10 mM EGTA, 0.01% BSA, pH 7.2 at 4&#x000b0;C. The homogenate was centrifuged at 2,000 g for 3 minutes and the supernatant transferred to a new tube and centrifuged at 12,000 g for 8 minutes. The resulting pellet was resuspended in a minimal volume of the isolation buffer devoid of EGTA.</p><p><bold>Skeletal muscle mitochondria</bold>. Hind-limb muscles were dissected in isolation buffer (300 mM sucrose, 50 mM Hepes, 10 mM Tris, 1 mM EGTA, 0.2% BSA, pH 7.2) at 4&#x000b0;C to remove fatty and connective tissue. The tissue was processed with a Polytron homogenizer and then with a mechanized potter. The homogenate was centrifuged at 850 g for 5 minutes and the supernatant was centrifuged again at 10,000 g for 5 minutes. The pellet was resuspended and centrifuged at 7,000 g for 5 minutes. The final mitochondrial pellet was prepared in a minimal volume of isolation buffer.</p><p><bold>Heart mitochondria</bold>. Hearts were minced finely in isolation buffer (300 mM sucrose, 10 mM Hepes, 2 mM EGTA, pH 7.2) at 4&#x000b0;C, in the presence of 0.5 &#x003bc;M type I protease (bovine pancreas) to release mitochondria from the muscle fibers, and then washed in the same buffer in the presence of 1 mg/mL BSA. The suspension was homogenized in a 40 mL tissue grinder and centrifuged at 800 g for 5 minutes. The resulting supernatant was centrifuged at 9,500 g for 10 minutes and the mitochondrial pellet was resuspended in a minimal amount of isolation buffer.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Mitochondrial H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> release</title><p>Mitochondrial H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> release was measured in 0.125&#x02013;0.500 mg protein/mL mitochondrial suspensions in experimental buffer (150 mM KCl, 10 mM Hepes, 2 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.1% BSA, pH 7.2) at 37&#x000b0;C, with continuous stirring in the presence of 25 &#x003bc;M Amplex Red and 0.5 U/mL horseradish peroxidase (HRP). Malate/glutamate, pyruvate/malate or succinate were used as substrates. Amplex Red is oxidized in the presence of extramitochondrial horseradish peroxidase bound to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, generating resorufin, which can be detected with a fluorescence spectrophotometer operating at 563 nm excitation and 587 nm emission [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Mitochondrial O<sub>2</sub> consumption</title><p>O<sub>2</sub> consumption was monitored using a Clark-type electrode, coupled to a high-resolution Oroboros respirometry system [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] in 0.125&#x02013;0.500 mg protein/mL mitochondrial suspensions under the same buffering conditions used in the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> assay.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Citrate synthase activity</title><p>Tissues were homogenized with an electric potter in 50 mM phosphate buffer (pH, 7.5) at 4&#x000b0;C and centrifuged at 600 g for 10 minutes, in the presence of protease inhibitor (1:100). A mixture of 100 mM Tris-HCl, 100 &#x003bc;M Acetyl-CoA, 100 &#x003bc;M DTNB, 250 &#x003bc;M oxaloacetate and 0.1% Triton-X, pH 8.1, was incubated with homogenate supernatant at 30&#x000b0;C for 5 minutes. CoA-SH produced by the enzymatic reaction reduces the DTNB, which is followed by the increase in absorbance at 412 nm (extinction coefficient = 13.6 mM<sup>-1</sup>&#x000b7;cm<sup>-1</sup>) (adapted from ref [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]).</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Immunoblots</title><p><bold>COX4 and NRF-1</bold>. Liver homogenates were prepared under the same conditions used for the citrate synthase assay and then diluted 4:1 in Laemmli buffer (100 mM Tris-HCl, 2% SDS, 10% glycerol and 0.1% bromophenol blue) for NRF-1 determinations. For COX4, homogenates were diluted in the same buffer, and heated at 100&#x000b0;C for 10 minutes. The proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose (COX4) or PVDF (NRF-1) membranes, which were then incubated with 5% BSA. Chemiluminescent detection was performed using primary anti-COX4 (1:1000), anti-NRF-1 (1:1000) antibodies and the respective secondary anti-mouse IgG (1:5000) and anti-rabbit IgG (1:5000) antibodies, both bound to peroxidase. The signals were quantified using ImageJ software and normalized by coloring the nitrocellulose and PVDF membranes with Ponceau and Coomassie Blue, respectively.</p><p><bold>Carbonylated Proteins</bold>. Tissue homogenates were prepared under the same conditions as the citrate synthase assay. A derivatization of the sample was performed, adding equal volumes of 24% SDS and 40 mM 2,4-dinitrophenylhydrazine (DNPH, prepared in 10% trifluoroacetic acid). The mixture, incubated in the dark for 30 minutes, allows the reaction between the DNPH and carbonyl groups in proteins. Samples were then treated with a neutralizing solution (1:3), of 2 M Tris, 30% glycerol and 19% 2-mercaptoethanol. The proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred to a PVDF membrane (adapted from ref. [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]).</p><p><bold>Nitro-tyrosin (NO<sub>2</sub>-Try) levels</bold>. Tissue homogenates were prepared under the same conditions as described for the citrate synthase assay. For dot blot experiments, 10 &#x003bc;L of homogenates containing 3 &#x003bc;g of protein were placed on nitrocellulose membranes. After they were dry, the membranes were blocked in a 4% BSA solution for one hour followed by an overnight incubation with primary anti-NO<sub>2</sub>-Try (1:2000). After one hour incubation with the anti-rabbit IgG (1:10000) secondary antibody, NO<sub>2</sub>-Try signals were identified using an Odyssey CLx system (LI-COR, Nebraska, USA). The signals were quantified using ImageJ software and normalized to protein levels by coloring the nitrocellulose membranes with Ponceau.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Antioxidant enzyme activities</title><p>Tissue homogenates were prepared as described for the citrate synthase assay. Glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px) activity was measured as described in ref. [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. A mixture of phosphate buffer, reduced glutathione (GSH), glutathione reductase (GR), EDTA, NADPH, NaN<sub>3</sub> and homogenate was used, and the reaction was initiated by the addition of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. The decrease in the quantity of NADPH was followed by absorbance at 340 nm for 3 minutes. The glutathione reductase assay followed the protocol described in ref. [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. GR catalyzes the reduction of GSSG to GSH in the presence of NADPH. The resulting GSH reacts with 5,5&#x02032;-dithio-bis-2-nitrobenzoic acid (DTNB), producing 5-thio-2-nitrobenzoic acid (TNB), detected by absorbance at 412 nm. The catalase assay was adapted from ref. [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Homogenates were incubated in the same experimental buffer used in the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> assay and the O<sub>2</sub> production rate was measured for 30 seconds after the addition of 200&#x02013;800 &#x003bc;M H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> using a Clark-type electrode at 37&#x000b0;C with continuous stirring.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Glutathione levels</title><p>The concentrations of GSH and GSSG, as well as total glutathione, were determined using a colorimetric assay with DTNB, as described in ref. [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. GSH reacts with DTNB producing TNB and GS-TNB, which is reduced back to GSH by GR. This process releases TNB, detected by absorbance at 412 nm.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Malondialdehyde (MDA) determination</title><p>Tissues were homogenized in TKM buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, 25 mM KCl and 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and SDS 10%, pH 7,5). One milliliter of thio-barburic acid (TBA; 0.4% w/v in 133 mM HCl) and 150 uL butylated-hydroxytoluene (BHT; 0.2% w/v in 95% ethanol) were added to 1.2 mL of the homogenate. The mixture was heated to 90&#x000b0;C for 45 min, cooled on ice, and extracted with isobutanol. The isobutanolic phase was injected through a Shimadzu auto injector model SIL-20A (Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) in a Shimadzu HPLC system consisting of two pumps; LC-20AT connected to a Luna C18 (Phenomenex, Torrance, CA) reversed-phase column (250 mm x 4.6 mm i.d., particle size 10 &#x003bc;m). The flow rate of the isocratic eluent (5 mM potassium phosphate buffer, pH 7, with 23% methanol) was 1 mL/min. A RF-10A/XL fluorescence detector was set at an excitation wavelength of 515 nm and an emission wavelength of 553 nm. The data were processed using the Shimadzu LC Solution 1.25 software. Malonaldehyde-bisdiethylacetal was used to calibrate the fluorescence data, yielding a quantitative adduct of the malonaldehyde-TBA product. The data were expressed as pmol of MDA normalized by protein mass (adapted from [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]).</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed using GraphPad Prism and Origin softwares. Figures are presented as average &#x000b1; standard error and comparisons were performed using two-tailed Student t-tests. p&#x0003c;0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec013"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec014"><title>IF reduces body mass and energy conversion efficiency</title><p>IF diets have been extensively shown to reduce body mass [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Indeed, we observed that, after a month, IF rats presented lower body weights than AL control rats (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). The decrease in body weight was a reflection of two additive effects of the diet: a 14% reduction in food consumption (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>) and a 40% decrease in energy conversion efficiency (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref>), or the amount of food ingested that results in weight gain. Similar decreases in energy conversion efficiency in IF have been reported previously and may be related to changes in hypothalamic energy metabolism control [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0120413.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120413.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Intermittent fasting promotes lower body mass related to a mild reduction in caloric intake and lower energy conversion efficiency.</title><p>(A) Average body weight per cage in (&#x025cf;) AL and (&#x02610;) IF animals after one month of treatment. (B) Cumulative food intake over one month of treatment. (C) Energy conversion efficiency. Data represent averages &#x000b1; SEM and were compared using <italic>t</italic> tests (n = 7 cages). ** p&#x0003c;0.01 vs AL. AL indicates <italic>ad libitum</italic> feeding, IF indicates intermittent fasting.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0120413.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>IF increases respiratory capacity in the liver, but not in other tissues</title><p>Restricted diets have been extensively shown to be related to changes in mitochondrial bioenergetics [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] which in turn are known to be determinant toward redox balance, since mitochondria are the most quantitatively relevant source of intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS). We thus sought to determine if short-term IF lead to changes in mitochondrial bioenergetics in different tissues.</p><p>In <xref rid="pone.0120413.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, we measured isolated mitochondrial NADH-linked oxygen consumption rates using samples obtained from different tissues under two conditions: state 3, in which ADP is present, stimulating maximal ATP synthesis-linked respiration; and state 4, in which the ATP synthase inhibitor oligomycin is present, and respiration reflects the magnitude of the proton leak [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Interestingly, respiratory rates in both states were unchanged by IF in the brain (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>), heart (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>) and skeletal muscle (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref>). On the other hand, both ADP-stimulated and oligomycin-inhibited respiratory rates were increased in liver mitochondria isolated from IF animals (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2D</xref>). This increase in respiratory rate was accompanied by a slight increase in respiratory control ratios (the ratio between state 3 and state 4 oxygen consumption) in IF samples, indicating that it reflects an increment in electron transfer capacity and is not a consequence of increased proton leak.</p><fig id="pone.0120413.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120413.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>IF induces an increase in respiratory capacity in liver, without bioenergetic changes in other tissues.</title><p>Oxygen consumption in isolated mitochondria from (A) brain, (B) heart, (C) skeletal muscle and (D) liver in the presence of 5 mM pyruvate plus 3 mM malate (A, B and D) or 2 mM glutamate plus 2 mM malate (C). State 3 was induced by the addition of 1 mM ADP and state 4 was achieved using 0.5 &#x003bc;g/mL oligomycin. The insert in Panel D represents respiratory control ratios (RCR), or state 3/state 4. Data represent averages &#x000b1; SEM and were compared using <italic>t</italic> tests (n = 4&#x02013;6 animals). * p&#x0003c;0.05 vs AL in the same respiratory state.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0120413.g002"/></fig><p>In order to further investigate the effects of IF on liver mitochondrial bioenergetics, we determined respiratory rates using succinate (which feeds electrons into the respiratory chain through Complex II; <xref rid="pone.0120413.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>) and TMPD-ascorbate (which reduces cytochrome c and cytochrome c oxidase; <xref rid="pone.0120413.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>). Both substrates also supported higher oxygen consumption rates in samples from IF animals, indicating that the enhanced respiratory capacity involves the enhanced activity of terminal electron carriers. Indeed, tissue levels of mitochondrial complex IV (cytochrome oxidase, COX, <xref rid="pone.0120413.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref>) were significantly enhanced in IF livers.</p><fig id="pone.0120413.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120413.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>IF promotes enhanced electron transport capacity in the liver.</title><p>Oxygen consumption in isolated mitochondria from livers in the presence of (A) 1 mM succinate plus 1 &#x003bc;M rotenone or (B) 200 &#x003bc;M TMPD plus 2 mM ascorbate. State 3 and state 4 were induced by ADP and oligomycin as described for <xref rid="pone.0120413.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>. (C) COX-IV and NRF-1 levels measured as described in Materials and Methods. (D) Liver citrate synthase activity, determined as described in Materials and Methods. Data represent averages &#x000b1; SEM and were compared using <italic>t</italic> tests (4&#x02013;6 animals). * p&#x0003c;0.05, ** p&#x0003c;0.01 vs AL.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0120413.g003"/></fig><p>The activity of the mitochondrial electron transport chain is often linked to an overall increase in the biogenesis of all mitochondrial enzymes. To test if this was the case, we determined the levels of NRF-1, a transcription factor that activates key mitochondria biogenesis, promoting mitochondrial DNA transcription and replication. Interestingly, NRF-1 levels were unaltered by IF (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref>). Confirming that liver mitochondrial biogenesis as a whole was not induced by IF, we found that activity of citrate synthase, a citric acid cycle enzyme and mitochondrial mass marker was equal in both groups (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3D</xref>). Altogether, these data suggests that IF induces an enrichment in respiratory chain proteins in liver mitochondria, without an overall increase in mitochondrial mass.</p></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>Mitochondrial reactive oxygen species release is unaltered by IF</title><p>In addition to determining changes in functional parameters, we measured the release of mitochondrial H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, a relatively stable and membrane-permeable ROS often used as a marker for oxidant production (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Interestingly, we found that IF did not significantly alter absolute H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> release in any tissue (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>), although liver release was slightly increased (p = 0.07). IF decreased relative H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>/O<sub>2</sub> release (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>) in liver due to the enhanced O<sub>2</sub> consumption observed in Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120413.g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0120413.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, and no change in this ratio was observed in other tissues. Since changes in respiratory rates and mitochondrial coupling are often determinant toward mitochondrial oxidant generation, this result is compatible with our finding that IF does not alter mitochondrial bioenergetic parameters in brain, heart and skeletal muscle. Furthermore, the lack of changes in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in liver are compatible with the prior finding that oxidant release in this tissue is not strongly regulated by respiratory rates and coupling [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0120413.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120413.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Reactive oxygen species production is not significantly altered by IF.</title><p>(A) H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> release by isolated mitochondria in the presence of 1 mM ADP (state 3) and 5 mM pyruvate plus 3 mM malate (brain, heart and liver) or 2 mM glutamate plus 2 mM malate (skeletal muscle). (B) Ratio between H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production and O<sub>2</sub> consumption by isolated mitochondria under the same conditions as panel A. Data represent averages &#x000b1; SEM and were compared using <italic>t</italic> tests (n = 4&#x02013;6 animals).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0120413.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>IF effects on antioxidants and oxidative damage are tissue-specific</title><p>Tissue redox status depends not only on the production of ROS but also on the levels and activities of antioxidant systems. We thus measured the activities of several key antioxidant enzymes in IF versus AL tissues (<xref rid="pone.0120413.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The activity of glutathione peroxidase (GPx) [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], which uses glutathione (GSH) as an electron source to reduce and remove H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, was significantly decreased by IF in the skeletal muscle, and unchanged in all other tissues. Glutathione reductase, which restores GSH, was unchanged by this dietary intervention, in all tissues. Catalase, which also removes H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, was decreased by IF in the brain and unchanged in the other tissues. Overall, our data indicate that IF does not increase antioxidant enzyme activity and, if anything, promotes some tissue-specific decreases in oxidant buffering capacity.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0120413.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120413.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Antioxidant enzyme activities.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0120413.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0120413.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Glutathione Peroxidase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AL</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6 &#x000b1; 1.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">119.9 &#x000b1; 9.94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238.2 &#x000b1; 13.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168.5 &#x000b1; 29.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mU<sup>&#x000b7;</sup> mg prot<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IF</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2 &#x000b1; 0.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.5 &#x000b1; 8.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195.0 &#x000b1; 11.50<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><bold>*</bold></xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174.8 &#x000b1; 9.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Glutathione Reductase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AL</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21 &#x000b1; 0.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52 &#x000b1; 0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.80 &#x000b1; 0.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.89 &#x000b1; 0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(mU<sup>&#x000b7;</sup> mg prot<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IF</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.48 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04 &#x000b1; 0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.48 &#x000b1; 0.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.02 &#x000b1; 0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Catalase</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AL</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.933 &#x000b1; 0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.742 &#x000b1; 0.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.841 &#x000b1; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(&#x003bc;mol<sup>&#x000b7;</sup> mg prot<sup>-1&#x000b7;</sup> min<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IF</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229 &#x000b1; 0.01<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn"><bold>*</bold></xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.850 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.954 &#x000b1; 0.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.738 &#x000b1; 0.10</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>Values are means &#x000b1; SEM and were compared using <italic>t</italic> tests (n = 4 animals).</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p>* p&#x0003c;0.05 vs AL. AL indicates <italic>ad libitum</italic> feeding, IF indicates intermittent fasting.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We also determined the levels of different forms of glutathione, an intracellular reductant and redox state marker (<xref rid="pone.0120413.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Levels of total glutathione (reduced plus oxidized), GSH, oxidized glutathione (GSSG) and GSH/GSSG ratios were mostly unchanged by IF, with a few exceptions: Livers of IF rats presented a significant increase in total glutathione and reduced GSH contents, which may be a consequence of a chronic exposure to a slightly increased oxidant generation (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>). On the other hand, IF hearts presented lower levels of GSSG and, consequently, elevated GSH/GSSG ratios (<xref rid="pone.0120413.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), an indicative of a more reduced intracellular environment.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0120413.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120413.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Glutathione levels.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0120413.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0120413.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total Glutathione</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AL</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.96 &#x000b1; 3.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.24 &#x000b1; 1.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.36 &#x000b1; 8.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.37 &#x000b1; 0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(nmol<sup>&#x000b7;</sup> mg protein<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IF</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.69 &#x000b1; 2.81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.63 &#x000b1; 0.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.61 &#x000b1; 14.57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.30 &#x000b1; 0.86<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GSH</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AL</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.06 &#x000b1; 3.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.57 &#x000b1; 1.81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.51 &#x000b1; 8.76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00 &#x000b1; 0.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(nmol<sup>&#x000b7;</sup> mg protein<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IF</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.68 &#x000b1; 2.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.44 &#x000b1; 0.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.95 &#x000b1; 13.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.70 &#x000b1; 0.43<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GSSG</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AL</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 &#x000b1; 0.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34 &#x000b1; 0.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.92 &#x000b1; 1.97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#x000b1; 0.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(nmol<sup>&#x000b7;</sup> mg protein<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IF</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.64 &#x000b1; 0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 &#x000b1; 0.15<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33 &#x000b1; 1.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 &#x000b1; 0.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>GSH/GSSG</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AL</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00 &#x000b1; 0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68 &#x000b1; 1.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25 &#x000b1; 1.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.36 &#x000b1; 2.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IF</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.04 &#x000b1; 0.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.45 &#x000b1; 1.60<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.03 &#x000b1; 0.89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.29 &#x000b1; 1.62</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>Values are means &#x000b1; SEM and were compared using <italic>t</italic> tests (n = 3&#x02013;4 animals).</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p>* p&#x0003c;0.05 vs AL. AL indicates <italic>ad libitum</italic> feeding, IF indicates intermittent fasting.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To determine the consequences of these tissue-specific modifications in antioxidant capacity, we measured the levels of protein carbonyls, MDA (a product of lipoperoxidation reactions) and nitro-tyrosine (NO<sub>2</sub>-Tyr) as markers for biomolecule oxidative damage (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). In keeping with the finding that IF hearts were in a more reduced state, as indicated by their GSSG levels (<xref rid="pone.0120413.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), we found that protein carbonyls and MDA levels were reduced by IF in this tissue (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5A and 5B</xref>). On the other hand, the brain presented enhanced protein carbonylation under IF, which may be a reflection of lower catalase activity. In the liver, a small decrease in the NO<sub>2</sub>-Tyr signal and a robust increase in protein carbonylation levels was observed. The protein carbonylation effect may be a consequence of the slightly enchanced in oxidant generation in this tissue. There was no dietary-promoted difference in the measured oxidative damage markers in the skeletal muscle. Altogether, these data suggest that short-term IF affects redox balance in a tissue-specific manner, promoting protection against oxidative damage in the heart and leading to enhanced protein carbonylation in the brain and liver.</p><fig id="pone.0120413.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0120413.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>IF changes oxidative damage to biomolecules in a tissue-specific manner.</title><p>(A) Carbonyl signals were quantified as described in Materials and Methods. (B) Malondaldehyde (MDA) levels were measured by HPLC as described in Materials and Methods. (C) Representative dot blots of NO<sub>2</sub>-tyr signals. (D) Average densitometric results for the dot blots presented in C. Data represent averages &#x000b1; SEM and were compared using <italic>t</italic> tests (n = 4&#x02013;5 animals). * p&#x0003c;0.05, ** p&#x0003c;0.01 vs AL.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0120413.g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec018"><title>Discussion</title><p>Dietary interventions that reduce body weight relative to <italic>ad libitum</italic> food intake have received extensive attention due to their mostly positive effects on age-associated diseases [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Since aging is often accompanied by increased oxidative tissue damage and loss of mitochondrial activity, many studies involving CR have focused on the bioenergetic and redox effects of this diet [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], mostly showing that it decreased oxidative damage [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. On the other hand, IF is less studied, and sometimes even confused with CR in the literature [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], so its bioenergetic and redox effects are less clear. We thus sought to determine the redox and bioenergetic effects of IF and found that this diet affects these parameters in complex, tissue-specific manners.</p><p>Perhaps the most studied tissue relative to the effects of IF is the brain. Both IF and CR have been related to healthier brain aging by reducing oxidative damage [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Indeed, IF in aged animals partially restores the loss of some antioxidant enzymes, and decreases 8-hydroxy-deoxyguanosine DNA adducts accumulated over time [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Thus, it was rather surprising to us to find that short-term IF in young animals leads to a significant increase in protein carbonyl signals in the brain of IF rats (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>), without measurable changes in mitochondrial function (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>), ROS release (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>), MDA or NO<sub>2</sub>-Tyr (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). This increased protein oxidative damage may be related to a small but significant decrease in brain catalase activity promoted by IF (<xref rid="pone.0120413.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). How this early increase in brain oxidative modifications relates to neurological protection in long-term IF models still remains to be uncovered, but the effects are most probably unrelated, since other neuroprotective dietary interventions do not see increments in oxidative damage markers in the brain even in short-term studies [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>IF and CR have also have been shown to protect the heart against ischemic injury [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. This protection has been attributed to activations in antioxidant defenses and stress response systems [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In fact, long-term IF has been shown to improve antioxidant defenses and oxidative biomarker levels in the heart [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Here, we show that IF has an impact on heart redox state very early on, preventing the oxidation of glutathione (<xref rid="pone.0120413.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), protein carbonylation and MDA formation (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).</p><p>Despite its central role in the control of energetic metabolism and aging, the skeletal muscle is still poorly studied regarding the effects of IF on redox state. Some long-term studies suggest that, unlike CR, IF may lead to a more oxidized state in this tissue, reducing antioxidant activity [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], increasing ROS production and oxidative protein modification [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Our short term study demonstrates that IF decreases glutathione peroxidase activity in the muscle (<xref rid="pone.0120413.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), although no changes are seen in glutathione redox state (<xref rid="pone.0120413.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) or oxidative damage markers (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Altogether, both our study and literature data suggest that IF does not prevent oxidative damage in the skeletal muscle and may actually worsen the redox condition of this tissue relative to <italic>ad libitum</italic> diets.</p><p>The liver is expected to be largely impacted by a dietary intervention such as IF, which alternates fasting periods with significant overeating. However, the few existent studies reporting IF effects on oxidative balance in the liver did not observe changes in antioxidant defense systems or in DNA and lipid damage [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Indeed, the same is observed for CR, in which most work indicates that there is no change in redox balance in the liver [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This finding may reflect the fact that ROS generation in the liver is not overtly modified by changes in metabolic conditions or respiratory substrates [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In this study, we find that short-term IF is actually detrimental toward liver oxidative balance, as reflected by the enhanced levels of protein carbonylation (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>) and induction of glutathione synthesis (<xref rid="pone.0120413.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), which may be related to a slight increment in mitochondrial H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> release (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>). Again, this indicates that not all restrictive dietary interventions with positive health-span effects produce immediate more favorable redox conditions in all organs.</p><p>Interestingly, short-term IF had very significant bioenergetic effects in the liver that were not observed in other organs: it increased respiratory capacity, irrespective of the substrate used (Figs. <xref rid="pone.0120413.g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0120413.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), but did not enhance overall mitochondrial biogenesis (<xref rid="pone.0120413.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). In a mouse model of IF in which more significant limitation in food intake occurred, IF was also found to increase liver respiratory capacity, but this effect was accompanied by mitochondrial biogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0120413.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The increased electron transport capacity of IF livers may be important to deal with the large fluctuations in metabolic demands in the liver under this dietary regimen, which alternates fasting periods (characterized by gluconeogenesis and &#x003b2; oxidation) with overeating (which promotes liver glycolysis and fatty acid synthesis).</p><p>Overall, our studies show that IF promotes complex and tissue-specific changes in mitochondrial bioenergetics and tissue redox state in a manner that is distinct from that observed in other restrictive dietary interventions. How these changes relate to both the desirable and deleterious long-term results of this dietary intervention, and how they relate to human responses to repeated fasting cycles, remains to be determined.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec019"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0120413.s001"><label>S1 Dataset</label><caption><title>Raw data.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0120413.s001.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to gratefully acknowledge Camille C. Caldeira da Silva and Edson A. Gomes for their exceptional technical support and Silvania Nunes for expert animal husbandry and maintenance.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0120413.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ravussin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<article-title>Caloric restriction in humans: impact on physiological, psychological, and behavioral outcomes</article-title>. <source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>287</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/ars.2010.3253">10.1089/ars.2010.3253</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20518700</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20518700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Speakman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<article-title>Caloric restriction</article-title>. <source>Mol Aspects Med</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.mam.2011.07.001">10.1016/j.mam.2011.07.001</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21840335</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21840335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nisoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tonello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cardile</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cozzi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bracale</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tedesco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Calorie restriction promotes mitochondrial biogenesis by inducing the expression of eNOS</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>310</volume>: <fpage>314</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16224023</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16224023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kowaltowski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Caloric restriction and redox state: does this diet increase or decrease oxidant production?</article-title><source>Redox Rep</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1179/1351000211Y.0000000014">10.1179/1351000211Y.0000000014</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22195991</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22195991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Remmen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<article-title>The effects of dietary restriction on oxidative stress in rodents</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2013.05.037">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2013.05.037</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23743291</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23743291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Cabo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<article-title>The diet restriction paradigm: a brief review of the effects of every-other-day feeding</article-title>. <source>Age (Dordr)</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11357-005-3286-2">10.1007/s11357-005-3286-2</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">23598600</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23598600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cerqueira</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kowaltowski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Commonly adopted caloric restriction protocols often involve malnutrition</article-title>. <source>Ageing Res Rev</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>424</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>430</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.arr.2010.05.002">10.1016/j.arr.2010.05.002</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20493280</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20493280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoelzel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<article-title>Apparent prolongation of the life span of rats by intermittent fasting</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. <year>1946</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>375</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21021020</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21021020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goodrick</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<article-title>Effects of intermittent feeding upon body weight and lifespan in inbred mice: interaction of genotype and age</article-title>. <source>Mech Ageing Dev</source>. <year>1990</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">2402168</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2402168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baur</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peshkin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Labinskyy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Resveratrol delays age-related deterioration and mimics transcriptional aspects of dietary restriction without extending lifespan</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>168</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2008.06.011">10.1016/j.cmet.2008.06.011</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18599363</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18599363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maudsley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<article-title>Caloric restriction and intermittent fasting: two potential diets for successful brain aging</article-title>. <source>Ageing Res Rev</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16899414</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16899414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Summer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Alternate day calorie restriction improves clinical findings and reduces markers of oxidative stress and inflammation in overweight adults with moderate asthma</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>674</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17291990</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17291990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cerqueira</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Cunha</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caldeira da Silva</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chausse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Long-term intermittent feeding, but not caloric restriction, leads to redox imbalance, insulin receptor nitration, and glucose intolerance</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1454</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1460</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2011.07.006">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2011.07.006</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816219</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Cabo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lyun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hagepanos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Intermittent fasting dissociates beneficial effects of dietary restriction on glucose metabolism and neuronal resistance to injury from calorie intake</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>6216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6220</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724520</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tahara</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Navarete</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kowaltowski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Tissue-, substrate-, and site-specific characteristics of mitochondrial reactive oxygen species generation</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1297</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2009.02.008">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2009.02.008</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19245829</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19245829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ferranti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kowaltowski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mitochondrial ATP-sensitive K+ channel opening decreases reactive oxygen species generation</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>536</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12586337</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12586337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>H&#x000fc;tter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Unterluggauer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garedew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jansen-D&#x000fc;rr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gnaiger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<article-title>High-resolution respirometry&#x02013;a modern tool in aging research</article-title>. <source>Exp Gerontol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>109</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16309877</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16309877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Srere</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<article-title>Citrate synthase</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source>. <year>1969</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shacter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<article-title>Differential susceptibility of plasma proteins to oxidative modification: examination by western blot immunoassay</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>1994</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>437</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">7835749</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7835749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Esworthy</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doroshow</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<chapter-title>Analysis of glutathione&#x02010;related enzymes</chapter-title> In: <source>Current Protocols in Toxicology</source>. <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>, <year>1999</year>; <volume>Chapter 7</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vierheller</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<article-title>Assay of glutathione reductase in crude tissue homogenates using 5, 5&#x02032;-dithiobis (2-nitrobenzoic acid)</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>. <year>1988</year>; <volume>175</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>413</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3239770</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3239770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<article-title>A method for assay of catalase with the oxygen cathode</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>. <year>1968</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>437</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">5723299</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5723299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kode</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<article-title>Assay for quantitative determination of glutathione and glutathione disulfide levels using enzymatic recycling method</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>3159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tatum</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghangchit</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
<article-title>Measurement of malonaldehyde by high performance liquid chromatography with fluorescence detection</article-title>. <source>Lipids</source>. <year>1990</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>226</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chausse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Solon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caldeira da Silva</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masselli Dos Reis</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manchado-Gobatto</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Intermittent fasting induces hypothalamic modifications resulting in low feeding efficiency, low body mass and overeating</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>2456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2466</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1210/en.2013-2057">10.1210/en.2013-2057</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24797627</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24797627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Caro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Torres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naudi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Portero-Ot&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Effect of every other day feeding on mitochondrial free radical production and oxidative stress in mouse liver</article-title>. <source>Rej Res</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>629</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/rej.2008.0704">10.1089/rej.2008.0704</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18593280</object-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<source>Bioenergetics 3</source>. <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>San Diego&#x02014;CA</publisher-loc>, <year>2002</year>; <volume>Chapter 5</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chausse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>da Cunha</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu&#x000e9;vano-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marazzi</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pessoa</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Mitochondrial compartmentalization of redox processes</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>2201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2208</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2012.03.008">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2012.03.008</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22564526</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22564526</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Valko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leibfritz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moncol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tesler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<article-title>Free radicals and antioxidants in normal physiological functions and human disease</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978905</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cerqueira</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kowaltowski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mitochondrial metabolism in aging: effect of dietary interventions</article-title>. <source>Ageing Res Rev</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.arr.2012.03.009">10.1016/j.arr.2012.03.009</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">22504406</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22504406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iba&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gredilla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barja</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<article-title>Dietary restriction at old age lowers mitochondrial oxygen radical production and leak at complex I and oxidativeDNA damage in rat brain</article-title>. <source>J Bioenerg Biomembr</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15906153</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15906153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Cabo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<article-title>Calorie restriction up-regulates the plasma membrane redox system in brain cells and suppresses oxidativestress during aging</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>19908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19912</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17167053</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17167053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<article-title>() Beneficial effects of intermittent fasting and caloric restriction on the cardiovascular and cerebrovascular systems</article-title>. <source>J Nutr Biochem</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15741046</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15741046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>FI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fasanella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tedesco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cavallini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bergamini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Peripheral lymphocyte 8-OHdG levels correlate with age-associated increase of tissue oxidative DNA damage in Sprague-Dawley rats. Protective effects of caloric restriction</article-title>. <source>Exp Gerontol</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>188</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15763395</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15763395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<article-title>Late-onset dietary restriction compensates for age-related increase in oxidative stress and alterations of HSP 70 and synapsin 1 protein levels in male Wistar rats</article-title>. <source>Biogerontology</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10522-009-9240-4">10.1007/s10522-009-9240-4</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19609710</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19609710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chandrasekar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colston</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<article-title>Calorie restriction attenuates inflammatory responses to myocardial ischemia-reperfusion injury</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>2094</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Castello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Froio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cavallini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Biasi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leonarduzzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Alternate-day fasting protects the rat heart against age-induced inflammation and fibrosis by inhibiting oxidative damage and NF-kB activation</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2009.10.003">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2009.10.003</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19818847</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19818847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>Retarding effect of dietary restriction on the accumulation of 8-hydroxy-2&#x02032;-deoxyguanosine in organs of Fischer 344 rats during aging</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9165299</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9165299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rad&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumiyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ookawara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Effect of aging and late onset dietary restriction on antioxidant enzymes and proteasome activities, and protein carbonylation of rat skeletal muscle and tendon</article-title>. <source>Exp Gerontol</source>. <year>2002</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1430</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12559411</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12559411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0120413.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Armeni</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pieri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saccucci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Principato</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<article-title>Studies on the life prolonging effect of food restriction: glutathione levels and glyoxalase enzymes in rat liver</article-title>. <source>Mech Ageing Dev</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>110</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9593316</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9593316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>