<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25751262</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4353720</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-19002</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Extracellular Superoxide Dismutase Regulates the Expression of Small GTPase Regulatory Proteins GEFs, GAPs, and GDI</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">SOD3-Regulated Expression of GEFs, GAPs, and GDIs</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laukkanen</surname><given-names>Mikko O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cammarota</surname><given-names>Francesca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>Tiziana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salvatore</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castellone</surname><given-names>Maria D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label><addr-line>IRCCS SDN, Naples, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Biomorphological and Functional Sciences, University of Naples Federico II, Naples, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label><addr-line>Institute of Experimental Endocrinology and Oncology (IEOS/CNR), Naples, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff004"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Molecular Medicine and Medical Biotechnologies, University of Naples Federico II, Naples, Italy</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Relvas</surname><given-names>Joao carlos Bettencourt de Medeiros</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>IBMC - Institute for Molecular and Cell Biology, PORTUGAL</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MOL MS MDC. Performed the experiments: MOL FC TE MDC. Analyzed the data: MOL FC TE MDC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MOL MS MDC. Wrote the paper: MOL MS MDC.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>mlaukkanen@sdn-napoli.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e0121441</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Laukkanen et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0121441.pdf"/><abstract><p>Extracellular superoxide dismutase (SOD3), which catalyzes the dismutation of superoxide anions to hydrogen peroxide at the cell membranes, regulates the cellular growth in a dose-dependent manner. This enzyme induces primary cell proliferation and immortalization at low expression levels whereas it activates cancer barrier signaling through the p53-p21 pathway at high expression levels, causing growth arrest, senescence, and apoptosis. Because previous reports suggested that the SOD3&#x02013;induced reduction in the rates of cellular growth and migration also occurred in the absence of functional p53 signaling, in the current study we investigated the SOD3-induced growth-suppressive mechanisms in anaplastic thyroid cancer cells. Based on our data, the robust over-expression of SOD3 increased the level of phosphorylation of the EGFR, ERBB2, RYK, ALK, FLT3, and EPHA10 receptor tyrosine kinases with the consequent downstream activation of the SRC, FYN, YES, HCK, and LYN kinases. However, pull-down experiments focusing on the small GTPase RAS, RAC, CDC42, and RHO revealed a reduced level of growth and migration signal transduction, such as the lack of stimulation of the mitogen pathway, in the SOD3 over-expressing cells, which was confirmed by MEK1/2 and ERK1/2 Western blotting analysis. Interestingly, the mRNA expression analyses indicated that SOD3 regulated the expression of guanine nucleotide-exchange factors (<italic>RHO GEF16</italic>, <italic>RAL GEF RGL1</italic>), GTPase-activating proteins (<italic>ARFGAP ADAP2</italic>, <italic>RAS GAP RASAL1</italic>, <italic>RGS4</italic>), and a Rho guanine nucleotide-disassociation inhibitor (<italic>RHO GDI 2</italic>) in a dose dependent manner, thus controlling signaling through the small G protein GTPases. Therefore, our current data may suggest the occurrence of dose-dependent SOD3&#x02013;driven control of the GTP loading of small G proteins indicating a novel growth regulatory mechanism of this enzyme.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by Fondazione SDN (decision number RC2010-M-0001, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sdn-napoli.it/">http://www.sdn-napoli.it/</ext-link>).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="22"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>Data is available in NCBI GEO (accession number GSE56546): Extracellular Superoxide Dismutase Regulates the Expression of GTPase Guanine Nucleotide Exchange Factors (GEFs), GTPase-activating proteins (GAPs), and Rho Guanine nucleotide disassociation inhibitor (GDI).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cell membrane-bound extracellular superoxide dismutase (SOD3) is one of the three SOD isoenzymes that catalyze the dismutation of superoxide radical (O<sub>2</sub><sup>.-</sup>) to hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Notably, both O<sub>2</sub><sup>.-</sup> and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> are second messengers in cell signaling [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] suggesting that the cellular effects of SOD3 are mediated by the local reduction of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>.-</sup> concentration and the simultaneous increase of the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration affecting the activation of the cell membrane-bound receptor tyrosine kinases (RTK), with a consequent impact on downstream growth and migration signaling [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Consistent with this hypothesis, several studies have demonstrated that SOD3 regulated growth and survival related signal transduction and gene expression [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], hence emphasizing the importance of this enzyme in growth regulation. Interestingly, <italic>SOD3</italic> expression is mildly upregulated in benign tumor model systems whereas it is downregulated in several cancers and in transformed cell lines [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] suggesting that the enzyme might be involved in the initiation of benign hyperplasia.</p><p>Based on our recent data SOD3 has a dose-dependent effect on cellular proliferation; low expression levels of SOD3 induce GTP loading on small GTPase proteins, mitogen signaling and cell proliferation, whereas high levels of SOD3 activate the DNA-damage response and the p53-p21 growth arrest pathway [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Although activation of the p53-p21 signal transduction pathway is likely to play a major role in growth limitation, high-dose SOD3&#x02013;inhibited proliferation was also observed in anaplastic thyroid cancer cells lacking functional p53 [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], indicating the existence of additional growth regulatory mechanisms.</p><p>Therefore, in the current study we focused on examining the effect of high-dose SOD3 on cell membrane-associated growth-regulatory molecules to identify the target molecules that translate the enzyme-based signaling to the cellular signal transduction network. According to our current data high-level SOD3 expression activated growth signaling through the cell membrane-bound receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs) and cytoplasmic non-receptor tyrosine kinases (TKs). However, simultaneously with the increased phosphorylation of RTKs and TKs, high-dose SOD3 decreased the level of expression of a number of growth-promoting genes, downregulated the activation of the RAS, RHO, RAC, and CDC42 small GTPases, and controlled the expression of the small GTPase regulatory genes encoding guanine nucleotide-exchange factors (GEFs), GTPase-activating protein (GAPs) and Rho guanine nucleotide dissociation inhibitor (GDI). These results could therefore clarify how SOD3 controls cellular proliferation and may additionally suggest potential drug targets for reducing carcinogenic growth.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Cell lines</title><p>8505c cells (DSMZ, German collection of microorganism and cell cultures, Braunschweig, Germany) modeling anaplastic thyroid cancer, were cultured in RPMI medium (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) supplemented with 10% FBS. Cell lines stably expressing human <italic>SOD3</italic> (kindly provided by Professor Stefan L. Marklund of the University of Ume&#x000e5;, Sweden), human <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> (Applied Biological Materials, Richmond, Canada), <italic>H-RasV12</italic> or the pcDNA3 <italic>GFP</italic> control plasmid were utilized. Cell lines were generated by nucleofection of 5 &#x003bc;g of the <italic>SOD3</italic> expression plasmid or the control plasmid into 5x10<sup>5</sup> cells, 5 &#x003bc;g of <italic>SOD3</italic>/1.5 &#x003bc;g of <italic>H-RasV12</italic>, and 5 &#x003bc;g of <italic>SOD3</italic>/1.5 &#x003bc;g of <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> transfection into 5x10<sup>5</sup> cells. The appropriate antibiotic selection was applied 48 hours after transfection and was continued for six weeks to create stable mixed cell populations. N-acetyl-cysteine (NAC) (Sigma) was applied to the 8505c cells at 2.5 mM daily.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Growth analysis</title><p>For the growth curve analyses 5x10<sup>3</sup> cells were seeded in the wells of 6-well plates in triplicate, and were counted daily until the cells reached a maximum of 70% confluence to avoid artifacts caused by cellular overgrowth. For the BrdU cell proliferation cell proliferation analyses, 10 mM bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) (Roche, Basel, Switzerland) was added to the growth medium for 15 min. Subsequently, the cells were fixed using an ethanol fix solution. The BrdU-positive cells were detected using FITC&#x02013;conjugated secondary antibodies (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories Inc., West Grove, PA). The nuclei were counter stained using Hoechst (Sigma) staining. Each cell count was performed in triplicate: each point represents the mean value for 3 samples.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Invasive growth in Matrigel</title><p>For outgrowth in Matrigel, 1x10<sup>3</sup> stably transfected SOD3 and control plasmid were mixed with 160 &#x003bc;l of Matrigel (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA) and were plated in 35 mm dishes containing glass coverslips. After the gel hardened, the cells were overlaid with 2 ml of growth medium and were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for up to 8 days.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Soft agar assay</title><p><italic>GFP</italic> control and <italic>SOD3</italic> transfected 8505c cells (5x10<sup>3</sup>) were plated in 6 cm gridded dishes with a bottom layer of 1% agarose and a top layer of 0.4% agarose constructed using complete growth medium. The plates were refreshed with complete medium twice a week. The number of colonies in each grid was counted at the 6-week time point. Each count was performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Protein arrays</title><p>Proteins were isolated from 8505c cells stably expressing <italic>SOD3</italic> or <italic>GFP</italic> control. Human phospho-RTK and phospho-kinase arrays (R&#x00026;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN USA) were performed using 300 &#x003bc;g of protein according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Signal density analysis was performed using ImageJ software GEL blot software.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Pull-down analysis</title><p>RAS, RAC, CDC42, and RHO pull-down analysis was performed using cells at 40% confluence in 10 cm dishes. After serum starvation for 24 h, the cells were lysed using ice-cold Rho-lysis buffer containing 20 mM HEPES (pH 7.4), 0.1 M NaCl, 1% Triton X-100, 10 mM EGTA, 40 mM glycerophosphate, 20 mM MgCl2, 1 mM Na3VO4, 1 mM dithiothreitol, a mixture of protease inhibitors, and 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride. The lysates were incubated for 15 min with a purified, bacterially expressed GST-fusion protein containing the CRIB domain of PAK1 (p21 activated kinase) that had been previously bound to glutathione-Sepharose beads, followed by three washes using Rho-lysis buffer. The GTP-bound forms of RAC1 or CDC42 associated with GST-CRIB were quantified through Western blotting analysis. GST-Rhotekin-RBD and GST-RAF1-RBD beads were used for RHO and RAS pull-down assay, respectively, and analyzed by Western blotting.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Western blotting analysis</title><p>The cells were homogenized in lysis buffer (50 mM/L HEPES pH 7.5, 150 mM/L NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1% Triton X-100, 1 mM/L EGTA, 1.5 mM/L MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM/L NaF, 10 mM/L sodium pyrophosphate, 1mM/L Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub>, 10 &#x003bc;g approtinin/ml, 10 &#x003bc;g leupeptin/ml) (Sigma). The following antibodies were used: &#x003b1;-RAS, &#x003b1;-RAC, &#x003b1;-CDC42, &#x003b1;-RHO, &#x003b1;-pEGFR, &#x003b1;-EGFR, &#x003b1;-pFAK, &#x003b1;-FAK, &#x003b1;-pSCR, &#x003b1;-SCR, &#x003b1;-pMEK, &#x003b1;-MEK, &#x003b1;-pERK1/2, &#x003b1;-ERK1/2, &#x003b1;-pAKT, &#x003b1;-AKT, &#x003b1;-pGSK3 &#x003b1; /&#x003b2;, &#x003b1;-GSK3 &#x003b1; /&#x003b2;, &#x003b1;-&#x003b2; catenin, &#x003b1;-pCHK2, &#x003b1;-CHK2, &#x003b1;-tubulin, &#x003b1;-SP1, &#x003b1;-pRET, &#x003b1;-RET (Cell Signaling, Danvers, MA, USA), and &#x003b1;-SOD3 (Santa Cruz, Santa Cruz, CA, USA). Signal density analysis was performed using ImageJ software GEL blot software.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>DNA damage assays</title><p>For &#x003b3;H2AX staining (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA) the cells were grown on coverslips, fixed using 4% PFA/PBS for 20 min at room temperature, permeabilized using 0.5% TritonX-100 and incubated with a primary antibody directed against &#x003b3;H2AX for 1h at RT. After several washes and labeling using the secondary antibody (30 min at RT), the cells were counterstained using Hoechst dye and were analyzed using fluorescence microscopy. Cells containing more than ten nuclear foci were considered positive.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Microarray</title><p>For the microarray expression analysis, the RNA was extracted from the 8505c cells in triplicate for use in cDNA synthesis. The analysis was performed at the Finnish Microarray and Sequencing Centre (FMSC), Turku Centre for Biotechnology, University of Turku, Finland. In brief, the array analysis was performed using an Illumina Human HT-12 v.3 Expression BeadChip that contained more than 48 000 types of probes according to the instructions of the manufacturer. Washing and scanning were performed according to the instructions in the Illumina BeadStation 500x manual (revision C). The Illumina expression data were extracted using BeadStudio version 1.5.0.34 software applying the default settings. The following quality assessments were applied to the samples: RNA quality control, quintile normalization of the sample data, inspection of the signal-intensity distribution, and sample correlation analysis. The threshold values for positive hits were selected based on the MA plot, and volcano blot comparisons were used to identify list the most differentially expressed array features. Three functional pathway analytical tools, the KEGG pathway signaling (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/pathway.html">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/pathway.html</ext-link>), GOrilla GO signaling pathway (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/</ext-link>), and GSEA gene enrichment programs were used to connect the gene expression patterns to cellular functions. The statistical analysis was performed using the R/Bioconductor6 open software package. The resulting gene list was filtered according to P G 0.001 (without adjustment for multiple testing). The genes were annotated, and output files were created using the biomaRt package. The selected positive hits were double-checked using quantitative RT-PCR.</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Gene expression analysis using real-time RT-PCR</title><p>The total RNA was isolated from the cells using an RNeasy minikit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). The first strand synthesis was performed using a QuantiTect Reverse Transcription kit (Qiagen) and quantitative PCR was performed using the SYBR Green PCR master mix (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). The primers are listed in <xref rid="pone.0121441.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Analysis of reactive oxygen species</title><p>Human 8505c control, 8505c SOD3, 8505c SOD3 Ras, and 8505c SOD3 GEF16 cells were grown on coverslips. Dihydroethidium (Sigma) and MitoTracker RED CMX (Invitrogen, Waltham, MA, USA) were added to the cells in 100 nM final concentrations. Cells were incubated 45 minutes at 37&#x000b0;C and washed with PBS. Images were analyzed with fluorescence microscope.</p></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Mouse transplantation</title><p>Human 8505c cells (10x10<sup>6</sup> cells) that were stably transfected with <italic>luciferase</italic> or <italic>SOD3</italic> were transplanted subcutaneously into two locations of the dorsal portion of female BALB/c nude (nu/nu) mice. The tumor size was assessed using a caliper at regular intervals and the tumor volume was calculated according to the following formula: (<italic>LxW</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup><italic>)/2</italic> (where L = length and W = width of tumor). The mice were sacrificed four weeks after transplantation and the tumors were isolated for RNA preparation (5). All of the animal procedures were approved by the Southern Finland Regional Experimental Animal Committee (License STH349A), and were performed according to the European Commission guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>The experiments were repeated at least three times. All of the results were expressed as the mean values &#x000b1;SD. The p-values (* = p&#x0003c;0.05, ** = p&#x0003c;0.01, *** = p&#x0003c;0.001) were determined using a one-way ANOVA with a Tukey-Kramer multiple comparison post-analysis test or, when appropriate, using two-tailed independent sample t-tests.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec016"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec017"><title>Robust <italic>SOD3</italic> over-expression reduced the rates of anaplastic thyroid cancer cell proliferation, invasion, and anchorage independent growth <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>We previously showed that robust SOD3 over-expression reduced the rate of cell proliferation by causing DNA damage, inducing the DNA-damage response, and activating the downstream p53-p21 signal transduction pathway of TPC1 papillary thyroid cancer cells, which have an intact growth-arrest signaling pathway. Notably, robust SOD3 over-expression also reduced the rate of cell proliferation of anaplastic thyroid cancer 8505c cells, which lack functional growth-arrest signaling [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Therefore, in the current study, we sought novel SOD3&#x02013;related signal transduction routes and the molecules that could transmit the SOD3-based extracellular signals to the cytoplasmic signaling network.</p><p>To evaluate the level of SOD3 synthesis, we determined the expression level of transfected <italic>SOD3</italic> using real-time RT-PCR and Western blotting which demonstrated high-level mRNA and protein production in anaplastic 8505c cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a-1c</xref>). To evaluate the effect of SOD3 over-expression on biological processes we studied the effect of SOD3 on the aggressiveness of these cancer cells. The growth curve analysis of anaplastic 8505c cells robustly over-expressing SOD3 demonstrated significantly (p&#x0003c;0.001) reduced cell numbers (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1d</xref>) and BrdU positive proliferating nuclei (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1e and 1f</xref>) compared with those of the control cells, consistent with our previous data [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Furthermore, the SOD3 over-expressing cells showed a reduced level of invasive growth in Matrigel (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1g</xref>) and colony formation in soft agar (p&#x0003c;0.001) as compared with those of the control cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1h and 1i</xref>). The data therefore suggested a reduced aggressiveness of the anaplastic thyroid cancer cells caused by high SOD3 expression.</p><fig id="pone.0121441.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Robust SOD3 expression reduced anaplastic thyroid cancer cell growth.</title><p>(a) Real time RT-PCR analysis showed a high-level mRNA production of <italic>SOD3</italic> transgene in anaplastic thyroid cancer 8505c cells. (b,c) Western blotting and related band intensity analysis showed high-level SOD3 production caused by <italic>SOD3</italic> transgene. (d) The growth curve analysis suggested significantly (p&#x0003c;0.001) decreased cell numbers in cells transfected with <italic>SOD3</italic>. (e,f) The BrdU DNA incorporation analysis confirmed significantly (p&#x0003c;0.001) decreased cellular growth caused by SOD3. (g) The 3-D gel invasion assay suggested almost complete lack of invasive capacity of 8505c SOD3 cells. (h,i) The soft agar analysis showed significantly (p&#x0003c;0.001) reduced formation of colonies suggesting decreased anchorage independent growth ability for SOD3 cells as compared to 8505c control vector transfected cells. (j) The growth curve analysis of control and SOD3 cells in the presence of 2.5 mM N-Acetyl-cysteine (NAC) showed growth reduction both in 8505c control and SOD3 expressing cells upon the treatment. (k) <italic>CATALASE</italic> mRNA expression. The quantitative RT-PCR showed no difference between 8505c control and SOD3 cells in <italic>CATALASE</italic> expression. Data are expressed as mean &#x000b1;SD. The p-values (* = p&#x0003c;0.05, ** = p&#x0003c;0.01, *** = p&#x0003c;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121441.g001"/></fig><p>Because SOD3 regulates the availability of superoxide anion and hydrogen peroxide reactive oxygen species, we tested the effect of the general ROS scavenger N-acetyl-cysteine (NAC), which mainly removes superoxide but can also reduce the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and nitric oxide (NO) concentrations, on cell proliferation. Noteworthy, O<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, and NO derivative peroxynitrate can increase growth by oxidative modification of MEK1/2-ERK1/2 signaling [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The growth curve analytical data showed reduced numbers of 8505c control cells in the presence of 2.5 mM NAC compared with those of the cells grown without NAC. This treatment even decreased the rate of proliferation of 8505c SOD3 over-expressing cells compared with that of untreated 8505c SOD3 cells, emphasizing the role of oxygen and nitrogen free radicals in this process (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1j</xref>). Interestingly, SOD3 over-expression had no impact on catalase expression (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1k</xref>) suggesting differential signal transduction for the enzymes.</p></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>SOD3 affected the activation of the cell membrane-associated receptor tyrosine kinases</title><p>SOD3 is a secreted molecule that interacts reversibly with the cell membrane-associated heparan sulfate proteoglycan molecules, such as collagen [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and fibulin-5 [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. To study the effect of high SOD3 expression on the phosphorylation of cell membrane-associated growth-related molecules we analyzed its effect on the activation of receptor tyrosine kinases. The dot intensity analysis of the phospho tyrosine kinase receptor array suggested an increased level of phosphorylation of epithelial growth factor receptor (EGFR), receptor like tyrosine kinase (RYK), anaplastic lymphoma kinase receptor (ALK), fms tyrosine kinase 3 receptor (FLT-3), ephrin A10 receptor (EPHA10), and v-erb-b2 avian erythroblastic leukemia viral oncogene homolog 2 (ERBB2, HER2) (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a and 2b</xref>), which are commonly activated in cancer cells [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In contrast, the level of phosphorylation of HGFR was reduced in the SOD3-positive cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a and 2b</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0121441.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>The phosphorylation status of receptor tyrosine kinases and cellular kinases in control plasmid and <italic>SOD3</italic> transfected cells.</title><p>(a,b) A receptor tyrosine kinase phosho-array showed increased levels of phosphorylation of FLT-3, EGFR, ERBB2, RYK, ALK, and EPHA10 in the 8505c SOD3 cells while HGFR activation was downregulated. Note, c-RET is not expressed in 8505c cells and therefore the signal represents unspecific labeling (<xref rid="pone.0121441.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>.). (c,d) Kinase phosphoarray for cytosolic non-receptor kinases and other signaling molecules. <italic>SOD3</italic> over-expression increased the activation of CREB, TOR, AKT, GSK3&#x003b1;/&#x003b2;, CHK2, and SCR family members SRC, FYN, YES, HCK, and LYN. Additionally, SOD3 induced &#x003b2;-catenin production. (e) A schematic representation of the main pathways that are affected by robust SOD3 over-expression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121441.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec019"><title>High SOD3 over-expression affected the activation of the AKT/GSK/&#x003b2;-catenin pathway, ERK1/2 pathway, and CHK2 kinase signal transduction pathways</title><p>The tyrosine kinase receptors transmit extracellular stimuli to membrane-associated non-receptor tyrosine kinases and small GTPases [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. To investigate the effect of SOD3 on the activation of intracellular signaling pathways, we evaluated the phosphorylation status of non-receptor tyrosine kinases using a phospho-kinase array. Based on the dot-intensity analysis of an array representing a selection of RTK downstream kinases, robust SOD3 expression induced the increased phosphorylation of SRC (Tyr419), LYN (Tyr397), YES (Tyr426), HCK (Tyr394), and FYN (Tyr420) (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c and 2d</xref>). SRC kinases are well-characterized proto-oncogenes that mediate the signaling between receptor tyrosine kinases and RAS [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], thereby inducing the activation of the mitogenic pathway, which leads to cellular proliferation. In addition, SRC activation induces the activation of the AKT-GSK3-&#x003b2;-catenin pathway, another major signal transduction pathway that mediates carcinogenic growth. The PI3K/AKT pathway together with the MEK/ERK signaling pathway is a crucial regulator of cell proliferation, survival and invasion. One of the substrates of AKT is the activation of the &#x003b2;-catenin signaling [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. AKT inactivates the destruction complex by phosphorylating glycogen synthase kinase-3&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; (GSK3&#x003b1;/&#x003b2;) at serines 21 and 9, thereby leading to the accumulation of &#x003b2;-catenin in the cytoplasm [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Subsequently, the cytoplasmic &#x003b2;-catenin is translocated into the nucleus, where it interacts with transcription factors to promote cell growth and carcinogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Our results suggest an activation of the AKT-GSK3-&#x003b2;-catenin pathway in SOD3 expressing cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c, 2d, and 2e</xref>). Lastly, consistent with our previous observations [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], the results of the kinase array assay indicated that high SOD3 over-expression led to the increased phosphorylation of CHK2 kinase (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c, 2d, and 2e</xref>), which is a component of the DNA damage response signal-transduction pathway and is frequently activated due to DNA-strand breaks [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p><p>To confirm the SOD3-mediated pathway activation indicated by the results of the protein array assay and to exclude the artifacts caused by nonspecific antibody binding (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0121441.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>.), we performed Western blotting analysis of SOD3 over-expressing cells and control cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a and 3b</xref>). The analysis confirmed that a robust SOD3 over-expression increased the level of phophorylation of EGFR, FAK, and SRC indicating that it activated cell membrane-associated RTKs and non-receptor tyrosine kinases. Notably, there was no activation of the downstream kinases MEK1/2 and ERK1/2 but rather a modest decrease in the level of their phosphorylation (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a and 3b</xref>), which was consistent with the reduced levels of cell proliferation (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1d, 1e, and 1f</xref>) and invasive growth (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1g, 1e, 1h, and 1i</xref>) suggesting the existence of a regulatory step in signal transfer between the SRC and MAP kinases.</p><fig id="pone.0121441.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Western blotting and DNA damage response analysis.</title><p>(a,b) Western blotting analyses supported the protein array data showing the increased activation of RTKs and non-receptor kinases in the <italic>SOD3</italic>-transfected 8505c cells. Note, MEK1/2 and ERK1/2 phosphorylation was moderately downregulated based on the band density analyses. (c,d) Western blotting and the related band intensity analysis for &#x003b2;-catenin nuclear and cytosolic proteins showed significantly (p&#x0003c;0.001) increased &#x003b2;-catenin production in cytosolic compartment. Tubulin was used to normalize cytosolic proteins and SP1 was used to normalize nuclear proteins. (e,f) &#x003b3;H2AX staining for 8505c cells suggested significantly (p&#x0003c;0.001) increased histone H2AX phosphorylation, suggesting DNA damages in 8505c SOD3 cells, which supported the increased CHK2 phosphorylation observed in protoarray and in the Western blotting. The white arrows in the control and the SOD3 merge panels indicate cells that are magnified to detect the nuclear foci. The white arrows in the control and the SOD3 magnification images indicate the nuclear foci. Data are expressed as mean &#x000b1;SD. The p-values (* = p&#x0003c;0.05, ** = p&#x0003c;0.01, *** = p&#x0003c;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121441.g003"/></fig><p>Our Western blotting data showed the robust activation of the AKT (Thr308) signaling protein in SOD3 over-expressing cells, consistent with our previous observations [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], which led to the phosphorylation of its substrate GSK3&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; at Ser21/9 and the accumulation of &#x003b2;-catenin (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a and 3b</xref>). Interestingly, the increased amount of cytosolic &#x003b2;-catenin was not accompanied by an increase in the amount of the nuclear fraction (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3c and 3d</xref>), again suggesting the existence of an inhibitory regulation occurring following strong SOD3 over-expression. Lastly, the Western blotting analysis confirmed the increased activation of CHK2 kinase (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a and 3b</xref>) upon SOD3 over-expression, which was accompanied by increased H2AX histone phosphorylation (&#x003b3;H2AX) (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3e and 3f</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec020"><title>Robust SOD3 over-expression had a significant impact on proliferation, migration, and invasion related gene expression</title><p>To gain a global view of the signaling pathways engaged by SOD3 to cause the reduced growth signaling and consequent reduced rate of cell proliferation, we analyzed the transcriptional alterations that occurred upon SOD3 over-expression by performing a microarray analysis of control plasmid and <italic>SOD3</italic> transgene transfected 8505c cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0121441.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref> Tables).</p><p>Analysis of our microarray data revealed that approximately 32% of the SOD3-mediated downregulated and upregulated genes were growth promoters or suppressors (45 of 136 and 20 of 61, respectively), emphasizing the connection between SOD3 and the growth-regulatory genes (Tables <xref rid="pone.0121441.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0121441.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Microarray Gene Ontology (GO) analysis indicated that of the 67 genes involved in the regulation of cell proliferation (GO:0042127), the expression of 24 genes was upregulated and that of 43 genes was downregulated (<xref rid="pone.0121441.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Table</xref>). Of the 33 cell proliferation-related genes (GO:0008283), the expression of 17 genes was upregulated and that of 16 genes was downregulated. In the group of genes involved in the regulation of cell migration (GO:0030334), the expression of 12 of the 27 genes was upregulated, whereas that of the remaining 15 genes was downregulated. Consistent with this result, of the 38 genes in the cell migration group (GO:0016477), the expression of 13 genes was upregulated and that of 25 genes was downregulated. Of the 18 genes in the positive regulation of locomotion group (GO:0040017), the expression of 8 genes was upregulated and that of 10 genes was downregulated. The regulation of cell motility group (GO:2000145) had 25 genes, of which the expression of 11 was upregulated and that of 14 genes was downregulated. Finally, the cell motility group of genes (GO:0048870) included 29 genes, of which 9 showed upregulated expression and 20 showed downregulated expression in the SOD3 over-expressing cells. Thus, the microarray-based functionality analysis indicated that robust SOD3 over-expression mostly downregulated the expression of genes involved in growth and migration.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0121441.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Growth-associated genes showing SOD3-mediated downregulated expression.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0121441.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0121441.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Growth promotors downregulated by SOD3</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definition</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AKR1C3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aldo-keto reductase family 1, member C3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_003739.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ang</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Angiogenin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001097577.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARHGEF16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rho guanine exchange factor (GEF) 16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_014448.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCNA1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclin A1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_003914.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSF2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colony stimulating factor 2 (granulocyte-macrophage)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001781.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELF3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E74-like factor 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004433.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DDIT4/REDD1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA-damage-inducible transcript 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_019058.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ERBB3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">v-erb-b2 erythroblastic leukemia viral oncogene homolog 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001982.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOXO1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forkhead box O1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002015.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCHFR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTP cyclohydrolase I feedback regulator</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005258.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAS3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyaluronan synthase 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005329.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL1&#x003b2;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interleukine 1&#x003b2;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_000576.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LTB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphotoxin beta</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002341.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAP3K8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase kinase 8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005204.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MSLN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesothelin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_013404.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NUAK2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNF1-like kinase, 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_030952.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NOX5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADPH oxidase 5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_024505.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDGFRL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet-derived growth factor receptor-like</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_006207.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RGL1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ral guanine nucleotide dissociation stimulator-like 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_015149.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLAT</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasminogen activator, tissue</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_000930.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stearoyl-CoA desaturase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005063.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRSS7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protease serine 7 (enterokinase)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002772.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RIPK4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Receptor-interacting serine-threonine kinase 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_020639.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RRAD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ras-related associated with diabetes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004165.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VEGFA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vascular endothelial growth factor A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001025367.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VCAM1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vascular cell adhesion molecule 1, CD106</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001078.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WNT7A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wingless-type MMTV integration site family, member 7A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004625.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Growth suppressors downregulated by SOD3</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definition</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BIRC3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baculoviral IAP repeat-containing 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001165.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BNIP3L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCL2/adenovirus E1B 19kDa interacting protein 3-like</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_014448.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCNG2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclin G2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004354.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFNA1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ephrin-A1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004428.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HRASLS3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HRAS-like suppressor 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_007069.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JUP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plakoglobin/&#x003b3;-catenin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002230.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KLF9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kruppel-like factor 9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001206.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LCN2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipocalin 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005564.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MTSS1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metastasis suppressor 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_014751.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDRG1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-myc downstream regulated gene 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005204.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCDH20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protocadherin 20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_022843.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASAL1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAS protein activator like 1 (GAP1 like)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004658.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASSF2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ras association (RalGDS/AF-6) domain family 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_170774.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASSF4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ras association (RalGDS/AF-6) domain family member 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_032023.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAT1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal transducer and activator of transcription 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_007315.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAT2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal transducer and activator of transcription 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005419.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YPEL3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yippee-like 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_031477.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VANGL2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vang-like 2/Van gogh</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_020335.1</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0121441.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Growth-associated genes showing SOD3-mediated upregulated expression.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0121441.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0121441.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Growth promotors upregulated by SOD3</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definition</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABCE1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP-binding cassette, sub-family E,1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001040876.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCND2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclin D2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_018404.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYR61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cysteine-rich, angiogenic inducer, 61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001554.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTPS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTP synthase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001905.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEF1A2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elongation factor 1 alpha 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001958.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ID1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibitor of DNA binding 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_181353.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ID3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibitor of DNA binding 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002167.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NMU</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neuromedin U</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_006681.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLAC8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placenta-specific 8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_016619.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Growth suppressors upregulated by SOD3</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definition</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARHGDIB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rho GDP dissociation inhibitor (GDI) beta</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_001175.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADAP2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ArfGAP with dual PH domains 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_018404.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DKK1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dickkopf homolog 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_012242.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPHB1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPH receptor B1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_004441.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSTM1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione S-transferase M1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_000561.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSTM2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione S-transferase M2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_000848.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HMOX1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heme oxygenase (decycling) 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_002133.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLK2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polo-like kinase 2 (Drosophila)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_006622.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RGS4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulator of G-protein signalling 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_005613.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">THBS1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thrombospondin 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM_003246.2</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>To validate the microarray data we selected 18 genes involved in growth, migration, and invasion (<xref rid="pone.0121441.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>.) and confirmed using real-time RT-PCR the SOD3-mediated alteration of gene expression. To cluster the genes involved in signal transduction pathways, we applied the categories of the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) finding 254 genes related to mitogen activated protein kinase (MAPK) signal transduction among the SOD3-regulated transcripts (<xref rid="pone.0121441.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Accordingly, the expression of 312 genes related to oncogenic pathways was affected upon <italic>SOD3</italic> over-expression. Consistent with the results of the KEGG analysis, the stimulated growth-related signaling cascades in SOD3 over-expressing cells that were identified by searching the Gene Ontology project (GO) indicated that cell proliferation and mitogen regulated pathways play a central role in the response to SOD3 over-expression (<xref rid="pone.0121441.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Finally, Gene Ontology (GO) analysis of the microarray data revealed the SOD3-mediated increased expression of the <italic>WWTR1</italic> and <italic>SNAI2</italic> genes, which are responsible for &#x003b2;-catenin cytoplasmic arrest [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and binding [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], respectively, in addition to the SOD3-mediated decreased expression of <italic>AXIN2</italic>, which drives the degradation of cytoplasmic &#x003b2;-catenin [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0121441.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). These data supported the results of the protein array and Western blotting analyses, which showed an increased level of &#x003b2;-catenin protein in the cytoplasm of SOD3 over-expressing cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3c and 3d</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0121441.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>The results of the KEGG, GO, and GOrilla functional analysis.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0121441.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0121441.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">KEGG signaling pathway analysis</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pathway</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p-value</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Genes</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pathway description</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4010</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">254</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAPK signaling pathway</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5200</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">312</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathways in cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5222</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small lung cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5215</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5219</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bladder cancer</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4012</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ErbB signaling pathway</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5210</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal cancer</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">GO pathway analysis</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pathway</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p-value</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Genes</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pathway description</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0001935</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endothelial cell proliferation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0001936</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of endothelial cell proliferation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0001937</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of endothelial cell proliferation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0001938</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive regulation of endothelial cell proliferation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0000083</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of transcription of G1/S-phase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0001558</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulation of cell growth</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0000279</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">308</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M phase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0000188</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inactivation of MAPK pathway</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1">Negative regulation of catenin import into nucleus SOD3 vs. Control</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GOrilla term</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p-value</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gene</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Function</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fold change</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">GO:0035414</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1">7.80E-04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WWTR1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-catenin cytoplasmic arrest</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNAI2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-catenin cytoplasmic binding</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AXIN2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-catenin cytoplasmic degradation</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.62</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The data indicated that SOD3 played a role in the regulation of the expression of genes involved in cell-proliferative pathways.</p></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>Robust SOD3 over-expression modified the expression of the small GTPase regulatory <italic>GEF</italic>, <italic>GAP</italic> and <italic>GDI</italic> mRNAs</title><p>Interestingly, our microarray data revealed changes in the levels of expression of guanine nucleotide exchange factors (GEFs), GTPase activating proteins (GAPs), and a Rho guanine nucleotide dissociation inhibitor (GDI) that were affected by SOD3 over-expression (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a, 4b, 4c, 4e, and 4f</xref>). GEFs are involved in the exchange of GDP for GTP, which activates members of the small G-protein superfamily of GTPases, whereas GAPs terminate the active state by inducing GTP hydrolysis [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. GDIs in turn inhibit the dissociation of GDP from small G-protein GTPases thereby maintaining these molecules in their inactive form [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Robust <italic>in vitro</italic> SOD3 expression downregulated the level of transcription of <italic>Rho guanine exchange factor 16</italic> (<italic>RHO GEF16</italic>), <italic>Ral guanine nucleotide dissociation stimulator-like 1</italic> (<italic>RGL1</italic>), and <italic>Ras protein activator like 1 (GAP1 like)</italic> (<italic>RASAL1</italic>) genes. Among the genes with upregulated mRNA expression in the SOD3 over-expressing cells, the most relevant GTPase-associated genes were <italic>RHO GDP dissociation inhibitor beta</italic> (<italic>RHO GDI2</italic>), <italic>ArfGAP with dual PH domains 2</italic> (<italic>ADAP2</italic>), and <italic>Regulator of G-protein signaling 4</italic> (<italic>RGS4</italic>), the latter one having also GAP activity (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a, 4b, 4c, 4d, 4e, and 4f</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0121441.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>SOD3 regulated the expression of small GTPase regulatory genes and affected the activation of small GTPases.</title><p>(a-f) Quantitative RT-PCR for GTPase superfamily regulatory genes. The panels show the expression levels of the regulatory genes <italic>in vitro</italic> cultured cells containing high-level <italic>SOD3</italic> mRNA and reduced growth abilities. (g-k) Pull-down assay for small GTPase proteins RAS, RAC, CDC42, and RHO. The assay suggested significantly (p&#x0003c;0.001) reduced GTP loading to each tested GTPase therefore being in line with reduced cell proliferation, migration, and growth related signal transduction. Data are expressed as mean &#x000b1;SD. The p-values (* = p&#x0003c;0.05, ** = p&#x0003c;0.01, *** = p&#x0003c;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121441.g004"/></fig><p>To link these data to the activation of small G proteins, we performed pull-down assays to evaluate the status of the small GTPase RAS, RAC, CDC42, and RHO, which showed a reduced level of small GTPase activation in the <italic>SOD3</italic> over-expressing cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4g, 4h, 4i, 4j, and 4k</xref>) supporting the observed decreased activation of the MEK1/2 and ERK1/2 mitogen activated signaling pathway and the decreased rate of cellular proliferation in these cells. These data hence indicated the existence of a major SOD3-related regulatory mechanism that affected the activation of the membrane-associated small GTPase molecule.</p></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>SOD3 over-expression regulates small GTPase regulatory gene mRNA production in a dose dependent manner</title><p>We previously demonstrated that the effect of SOD3 on the expression of growth-related genes correlated with the level of expression of this enzyme <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. A robust SOD3 expression caused growth arrest, whereas a moderately increased SOD3 production supported cell survival, growth and tumorigenesis [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In the current study, we evaluated mice that had been previously transplanted with 8505c cells transfected with the <italic>luciferase</italic> expression control vector or <italic>SOD3</italic> expression vector [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] to study the effect of low-dose growth promoting SOD3 synthesis levels on the expression of GEFs, GAPs, and GDIs (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a and 5b</xref>). While the <italic>in vitro</italic> expression of GTPase regulatory genes favored the reduced growth rate and the inactivation of small GTPases (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a, 4b, 4c, 4d, 4e, and 4f</xref>), the level of mRNA expression of <italic>GEF</italic>, <italic>GAP</italic>, and <italic>GDI</italic> genes <italic>in vivo</italic> isolated tumors was reversed (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c, 5d, 5e, 5f, 5g, and 5h</xref>) supporting the observation of low SOD3 level induced increased rate of tumor growth (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5b</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Although a significantly decreased expression of the <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> and <italic>RAL GEF RGL1</italic> genes was observed <italic>in vitro</italic> in the 8505c SOD3 over-expressing cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a and 4b</xref>), the level of expression of these genes was increased in tumors that showed a moderate expression level of SOD3 <italic>mRNA</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5c and 5d</xref>). Similarly, the significantly increased expression of the GTPase activator proteins <italic>Arf GAP ADAP2</italic> and <italic>RGS4</italic> was correlated with a high level of <italic>SOD3</italic> expression <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4c and 4e</xref>) and was markedly decreased in the <italic>in vivo</italic> tumors (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5e and 5g</xref>). Finally, the expression of <italic>RHO GDI 2</italic>, of which increased mRNA levels were found <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4f</xref>), was downregulated <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5h</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0121441.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title><italic>In vivo</italic> transplantation of 8505c SOD3 cells results in tumorigenesis.</title><p>(a) There was a robust over-production of <italic>SOD3</italic> mRNA in 8505c SOD3 stable cells while the tumors derived from 8505c SOD3 stable cells contained moderately increased <italic>SOD3</italic> mRNA consistent with our previously published data. (b) Bioluminescence imaging showing the increased tumor size in 8505c SOD3 transplanted mice as compared to control cell transplanted animals. (c-h) <italic>GEF</italic>, <italic>GAP</italic>, and <italic>GDI</italic> mRNA expression <italic>in vivo</italic>. The mice showing a moderately increased SOD3 expression in transplanted 8505c cells had reversed small GTPase regulatory gene expression as compared to <italic>in vitro</italic> situation. Data are expressed as mean &#x000b1;SD. The p-values (* = p&#x0003c;0.05, ** = p&#x0003c;0.01, *** = p&#x0003c;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121441.g005"/></fig><p>To dissect the effects of SOD3 on the expression of the small GTPase regulatory genes, we investigated the functional effects of <italic>RAS</italic> and <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> over-expression in <italic>SOD3</italic> transfected cells. Our data demonstrated that the stable expression of the <italic>H-RasV12</italic> oncogene in 8505c <italic>SOD</italic>3 cells reverted the SOD3-mediated growth inhibitory effect, confirming the negative regulation of RAS by SOD3 (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4g and 4h</xref>) and suggesting a role for RAS as a mediator of SOD3 function, as previously described (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6a</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Analysis of the invasive capability as determined using 3D Matrigel assay confirmed the ability of <italic>H-RasV12</italic> to revert the growth inhibition of SOD3 cells to the levels of 8505c control cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6b</xref>). Similarly to the effect of <italic>H-RasV12</italic> expression, the over-expression of the <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> gene in 8505c SOD3 cells caused an increased level of cell proliferation compared with that of the 8505c control and 8505c SOD3 cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6c, 6d, and 6e</xref>). The data suggests that SOD3-mediated inhibition of <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> expression is an important step in the SOD3-mediated regulation of cell growth, which supports previous observations concerning the oncogenic character of <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In contrast, RNAi of <italic>RGS4</italic> expression had no effect on the growth potential of SOD3 expressing cells, suggesting that modulation of a single gene encoding a protein with GAP activity was insufficient to inhibit the effects of SOD3 over-expression (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6f, 6g, and 6h</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0121441.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121441.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Reversed growth characteristics by <italic>H-RasV12</italic> and <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> over-expression in <italic>SOD3</italic> transfected cells.</title><p>(a,b) The 8505c SOD3 cells were stable transfected with <italic>H-RasV12</italic> oncogene and analyzed by growth curve and 3-D invasion analysis. Both analysis suggested marked increase in the growth of SOD3 cells after <italic>H-RasV12</italic> transfection. (c) The 8505c SOD3 cells were stably transfected with <italic>RHO GEF16</italic>. The real time RT-PCR suggested significant (p&#x0003c;0.01) increase in <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> mRNA production that was confirmed by Western blotting (lower panel). (d,e) The BrdU DNA incorporation analysis showed significantly (p&#x0003c;0.001) increased nuclear proliferation after <italic>RHO GEF16</italic> over-expression as compared to 8505c SOD3 cells. (f) The RNAi of <italic>RGS4</italic> in 8505c SOD3 cells showed significant downregulation of <italic>RGS4</italic> mRNA production. (g,h) However, the BrdU DNA incorporation analysis failed to show differences between 8505c control and 8505c SOD3/siRGS4 cells. (i) A schematic drawing hypothesizing the SOD3 action in the cells. SOD3 over-expression activates cell membrane RTKs and membrane associated non-receptor tyrosine kinases. Depending on the expression level of <italic>SOD3</italic> the proliferative and migratory signal is either halted or promoted at the level of small GTPase regulatory genes and small GTPases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121441.g006"/></fig><p>The 8505c control, 8505c SOD3, 8505c SOD3 Ras, and in 8505c SOD3 GEF16 cells were stained with dihydroethidium (DHE) and with MitoTracker RED CMX. DHE staining of live cells suggested no difference between 8505c control and 8505c SOD3 cells, a modest increase in cytoplasmic staining in 8505c SOD3 Ras cells as compared to control cells and a marked increased stainining in 8505c SOD3 GEF16 cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig</xref>.). MitoTracker RED CMX staining suggested similar mitochondrial staining in the all cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig</xref>.).</p><p>In summary, our data revealed a dose-dependent effect of SOD3 on the activity of small GTPase regulatory genes. These data clarified the correlation between high SOD3 expression levels and reduced cell proliferation, colony formation, and cell migration. These effects are regulated by a large set of genes that appear to converge on the small GTPase regulatory genes (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6i</xref>), &#x003b2;-catenin, and growth promoting/suppressing genes.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec023"><title>Discussion</title><p>Reactive oxygen species O<sub>2</sub><sup>.-</sup> and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, which were originally thought to be harmful free radicals, are important second messengers in cellular signaling. The primary reactive oxygen species O<sub>2</sub><sup>.-</sup> is a precursor to a number of secondary radicals, such as H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, which can induce DNA damage, lipid peroxidation, and protein oxidation [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Noteworthy, at a low physiological concentration, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> functions as a growth stimulator that increases the rate of cell proliferation whereas at high concentrations, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> has toxic effects on cellular functions [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Superoxide dismutases (SODs) have been traditionally classified as antioxidative enzymes that remove harmful O<sub>2</sub><sup>.-</sup> radicals, producing more stable, although still reactive, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> molecules. Thus SODs regulate the availability of O<sub>2</sub><sup>.-</sup> and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and should be considered intermediary molecules between oxidative free radical-forming enzymes and antioxidative free radical removing enzymes.</p><p>A recent report demonstrated that SOD3 acted as a growth regulator suggesting its ability to affect RAS activation and to stimulate mitogenic growth signaling [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, the mechanism for SOD3&#x02014;derived RAS activation is poorly characterized. In the present work we analyzed the effect of high SOD3 expression on the phosphorylation status of the cell membrane-associated RTKs and the cytoplasmic non-receptor kinases as well as on the transcriptome to achieve a global view of the transcriptional changes occurring during SOD3 expression. Consistent with the results of previous studies, our functional analysis showed that robust SOD3 expression reduced cellular growth (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Interestingly, high-level SOD3 expression markedly increased the activation of the cell membrane-associated RTKs and the downstream signaling molecules, such as the SRC protein family members SRC, FYN, YES, HCK, and LYN (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) all of which function upstream of the small GTPase proteins, such as RAS [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. More interestingly, the greatly increased level of SRC family signaling in 8505c SOD3 cells did not increase the activation status of small GTPase proteins as compared to control cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>); in contrast, the levels of activation of these proteins in the former cells were moderately decreased thus confirming our earlier observations that SOD3 regulates mitogen signaling at the level of RAS GTPase [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The neutralization of the activity of the mitogen signal transduction pathway (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a and 3b</xref>) was associated with the modification of &#x003b2;-catenin signaling, suggesting that the reduced nuclear localization of &#x003b2;-catenin in SOD3 over-expressing cells (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a, 3b, 3c, and 3d</xref>) and the simultaneous DDR activation (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a, 3b, 3e, and 3f</xref>) enhanced the resultant decrease in the rate of cell proliferation observed in the cell proliferation and cell migration experiments (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>The involvement of SOD3 in the growth-regulated signal transduction was confirmed by the microarray screening combined with KEGG, GO, and GOrilla functional analyses (<xref rid="pone.0121441.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The microarray results further demonstrated the SOD3&#x02013;driven regulation of the genes responsible for the activation of small GTPases. Most importantly, the screening indicated that SOD3 regulated the expression of six GEFs, GAPs, and GDIs (Figs. <xref rid="pone.0121441.g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0121441.g005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) that together with the downregulated growth promoters, and the upregulated growth suppressors (Tables <xref rid="pone.0121441.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0121441.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref>, and <xref rid="pone.0121441.t003" ref-type="table">3</xref>) could have caused decreased mitogen signaling despite the presence of a strong upstream mitogen stimulus. Noteworthy, the simultaneous expression of SOD3 and RAS or SOD3 and RHO GEF16 increased the rate of cellular growth to the levels of the control cells strengthening the hypothesis that RAS and RHO GEF16 are mediators of the SOD3 effect on growth and migration (<xref rid="pone.0121441.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>).</p><p>Small GTPases play pivotal roles in the regulation of the cytoskeletal rearrangements and cell motility, but are also involved in cell proliferation, transformation and differentiation, and participate in many steps for carcinogenesis initiation and the progression of cancers. Once bound to the cell membrane, the GTPase superfamily members interact with the upstream stimulators, such as SRC family proteins, and the cytoplasmic molecules that tightly are regulating their activity [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The activation of small GTPases requires GDP-GTP exchange, which is catalyzed by various guanine nucleotide exchange factors (GEFs) [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In contrast, GTPase-activating proteins (GAPs) inactivate small GTPases by stimulating the hydrolysis of GTP [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Inactive GTPases are sequestered in the cytosol by the guanine nucleotide dissociation inhibitors (GDI) [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Due to their ability to increase the activity of small GTPase superfamily, GEFs are potential oncogenes that affect tumorigenesis, e.g. RAL GEFs have been shown to increase the anchorage independent growth <italic>in vitro</italic> and the transformation activity after their membrane translocation [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p><p>GAPs activate the intrinsic GTPase activity of Ras superfamily GTPase members, which hydrolyze GTP and return the GTPase to the inactive GDP bound form. Interestingly, GAPs can hydrolyze only the wild-type RAS to terminate its signaling, whereas these molecules have no effect on mutant RAS activity, therefore being less attractive drug targets [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. However, several studies have shown the tumor suppressive properties of GAPs [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] hence suggesting that they play a role in early stages of tumorigenesis.</p><p>The third group of regulators is GDIs, which maintain the GTPases in GDP-bound inactive form in the cytosolic compartment and control their GTPase membrane-binding capacity. RHO GDI2 has been shown to be a metastasis suppressor in bladder and breast cancers [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. In line, the level of RHO GDI2 expression was increased during the early phase of breast epithelial hyperplasia and was significantly decreased in transformed metastatic cells. Indeed, it has been shown that RHO GDI2 reduced the extend of cell migration and served as a metastasis inhibitor rather than a cell proliferation suppressor [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].</p><p>We have recently demonstrated that SOD3 has a dose-dependent effect on cellular growth <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. High-level SOD3 expression decreased the growth rate by inducing apoptosis in p53 responsive cancer cells whereas a moderately upregulated level of SOD3 production increased the proliferation of primary and cancer cells, and promoted cellular immortalization and neoplastic transformation. Noteworthy, the induction of p53 activation and the resultant growth arrest were observed in both in primary cells and in cancer cells containing functional p53 response. Furthermore, the p53 induction occurred at both at low and high <italic>SOD3</italic> expression levels: the response induced by high-level <italic>SOD3</italic> expression was the immediate death of most of the cells within 24 hours, whereas low-level <italic>SOD3</italic> expression first activated a proliferative burst that was followed by DNA strand break stimulated p53-p21 growth arrest and a senescence phase in a fashion similar to that caused by the <italic>H-RasV12</italic> oncogene [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, the growth arrest pathway activation does not solely explain this reduced cellular growth. A number of <italic>in vivo</italic> SOD3 mouse model studies have demonstrated the decreased level of tumorigenesis under both p53-responsive and p53-inactive conditions, supporting our recent <italic>in vitro</italic> data [<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121441.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and indicating the existence of additional growth-signaling-related regulatory systems. Therefore, the current data showing decreased <italic>GEF</italic> expression and increased <italic>GAP</italic> and <italic>GDI</italic> production, which paralleled with a reduced activation of small GTPases at high SOD3 levels, together with the observed effects on &#x003b2;-catenin signaling supported the previous observations and may explain how robust SOD3 expression reduces cellular growth. In turn, a moderately increased <italic>SOD3</italic> mRNA expression reversed the <italic>GEF</italic>, <italic>GAP</italic>, and <italic>GDI</italic> synthesis suggesting the regulatory characteristics of SOD3 in controlling the activation the status of small GTPases.</p><p>Our current and previous data thus suggest that SOD3 has a dose-dependent effect on growth signaling. A moderate level of SOD3 expression induced proliferative signal transduction through phophorylation of the RTKs and cytosolic non-receptor kinases, leading to RAS and ERK activation. In contrast, high SOD3 levels reduced the rates of cell proliferation and cell migration by affecting the expression of a family of small GPTase regulatory genes that negatively regulate the activity of small GTPases and ERK kinases. These data revealed a new scenario, in which SOD3 acts in a dose-dependent manner to simultaneously activate distinct pathways that have conflicting effects. Because SOD3 itself is a drug target of great interest, the current study might indicate molecules that mediate the effects of SOD3 on cell proliferation and hence are potential druggable targets in the early phase of tumorigenesis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec024"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121441.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Western blotting analysis showing a false positive signal.</title><p>RET and phospho-RET Western blotting from 8505c cells showed no RET expression. The bands observed in the p-RET lane are the result of nonspecific labeling.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121441.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121441.s002"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><title>Quantitative RT-PCR validation for the microarray.</title><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121441.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121441.s003"><label>S3 Fig</label><caption><title>Reactive oxygen staining from live cells.</title><p>(a) The images show Hoechst nuclear staining and DHE ROS staining. DHE staining of the cells shows minor differences in ROS staining in 8505c SOD3 as compared to 8505c control cells. A moderate increase was observed in 8505c SOD3 Ras cells and a marked increased in 8505c SOD3 GEF16 cells. (b) Mitochondrial ROS staining showed no differences between cell lines. Images are shown in grey scale (left side panes) and with red fluorescence (right side panels).</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121441.s003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121441.s004"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Primer sequences used for quantitative RT-PCR.</title><p>(XLSX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121441.s004.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121441.s005"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>SOD3&#x02014;derived down-regulation of genes analyzed by microarray.</title><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121441.s005.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121441.s006"><label>S3 Table</label><caption><title>SOD3&#x02014;derived upregulation of genes analyzed by microarray.</title><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121441.s006.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121441.s007"><label>S4 Table</label><caption><title>Functional classification of genes using Gene Ontology (GO) analysis.</title><p>(XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121441.s007.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0121441.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marklund</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<article-title>Human copper-containing superoxide dismutase of high molecular weight</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>7634</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">6961438</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6961438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Irani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goldschmidt-Clermont</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Ras, superoxide and signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>1339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10076523</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10076523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Driessens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Deken</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Detours</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corvilain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Roles of hydrogen peroxide in thyroid physiology and disease</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>3764</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17666482</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17666482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laurila</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laatikainen</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castellone</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laukkanen</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>
<article-title>SOD3 reduces inflammatory cell migration by regulating adhesion molecule and cytokine expression</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e5786</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0005786">10.1371/journal.pone.0005786</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19495415</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19495415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Castellone</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Langella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cantara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laurila</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laatikainen</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bellelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Extracellular Superoxide Dismutase Induces Mouse Embryonic Fibroblast Proliferative Burst, Growth Arrest, Immortalization, and Consequent In Vivo Tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1460</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/ars.2013.5475">10.1089/ars.2013.5475</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24328532</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24328532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laurila</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castellone</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Curcio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laatikainen</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haaparanta-Solin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gronroos</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Extracellular superoxide dismutase is a growth regulatory mediator of tissue injury recovery</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>448</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/mt.2008.282">10.1038/mt.2008.282</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19107121</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19107121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sibenaller</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Witmer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schrock</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Extracellular superoxide dismutase suppresses hypoxia-inducible factor-1alpha in pancreatic cancer</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2014.02.002">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2014.02.002</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24509158</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24509158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laatikainen</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Incoronato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castellone</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laurila</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laukkanen</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>
<article-title>SOD3 decreases ischemic injury derived apoptosis through phosphorylation of Erk1/2, Akt, and FoxO3a</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e24456</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0024456">10.1371/journal.pone.0024456</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21909393</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21909393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>
<article-title>Superoxide dismutase 3 suppresses hyaluronic acid fragments mediated skin inflammation by inhibition of toll-like receptor 4 signaling pathway: superoxide dismutase 3 inhibits reactive oxygen species-induced trafficking of toll-like receptor 4 to lipid rafts</article-title>. <source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>313</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1089/ars.2011.4066">10.1089/ars.2011.4066</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21957979</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21957979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nozik-Grayck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suliman</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Majka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albietz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Rheen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roush</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Lung EC-SOD overexpression attenuates hypoxic induction of Egr-1 and chronic hypoxic pulmonary vascular remodeling</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>295</volume>:<fpage>L422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1152/ajplung.90293.2008">10.1152/ajplung.90293.2008</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18599502</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18599502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teoh</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oberley</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Domann</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
<article-title>Overexpression of extracellular superoxide dismutase attenuates heparanase expression and inhibits breast carcinoma cell growth and invasion</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>6355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-1195">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-1195</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19602586</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19602586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laatikainen</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castellone</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hebrant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoste</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cantisani</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laurila</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Extracellular superoxide dismutase is a thyroid differentiation marker down-regulated in cancer</article-title>. <source>Endocr Relat Cancer</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>785</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1677/ERC-10-0021">10.1677/ERC-10-0021</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576801</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Svensk</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paakko</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hiravikoski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kinnula</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>
<article-title>Differential expression of superoxide dismutases in lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Pathol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>122</volume>:<fpage>395</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>404</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15362370</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15362370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pesse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levrand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feihl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waeber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gavillet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pacher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (2005) <article-title>Peroxynitrite activates ERK via Raf-1 and MEK, independently from EGF receptor and p21Ras in H9C2 cardiomyocytes</article-title>. <source>J Mol Cell Cardiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15850570</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15850570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oury</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ostergaard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valnickova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wegrzyn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thogersen</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Extracellular superoxide dismutase (EC-SOD) binds to type i collagen and protects against oxidative fragmentation</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>279</volume>:<fpage>13705</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14736885</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14736885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jeney</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ushio-Fukai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Fibulin-5 is a novel binding protein for extracellular superoxide dismutase</article-title>. <source>Circ Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>1067</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528465</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ciardiello</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saeki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dono</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Persico</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plowman</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Differential expression of epidermal growth factor-related proteins in human colorectal tumors</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>7792</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1715580</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1715580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanafusa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanafusa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<article-title>A novel oncogene, v-ryk, encoding a truncated receptor tyrosine kinase is transduced into the RPL30 virus without loss of viral sequences</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>5975</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">1527848</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1527848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirstein</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dittmer</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saltman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Fusion of a kinase gene, ALK, to a nucleolar protein gene, NPM, in non-Hodgkin's lymphoma</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>263</volume>:<fpage>1281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8122112</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8122112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Timeus</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricotti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crescenzio</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spinelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Flt-3 and its ligand are expressed in neural crest-derived tumors and promote survival and proliferation of their cell lines</article-title>. <source>Lab Invest</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1025</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11454991</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11454991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tabone</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kandpal</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<article-title>Potential clinical relevance of Eph receptors and ephrin ligands expressed in prostate carcinoma cell lines</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>342</volume>:<fpage>1263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16516143</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16516143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benovic</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Regulation of transmembrane signaling by receptor phosphorylation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>913</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3030559</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3030559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <article-title>Johnson FM Regulation of SRC family kinases in human cancers</article-title>. <source>J Signal Transduct</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>2011</volume>:<fpage>865819</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2011/865819">10.1155/2011/865819</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21776389</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21776389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<article-title>Wnt signaling to beta-catenin involves two interactive components. Glycogen synthase kinase-3beta inhibition and activation of protein kinase C</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>17894</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10749878</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10749878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alessi</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andjelkovich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hemmings</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<article-title>Inhibition of glycogen synthase kinase-3 by insulin mediated by protein kinase B</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>378</volume>:<fpage>785</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8524413</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8524413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elledge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Linkage of ATM to cell cycle regulation by the Chk2 protein kinase</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>282</volume>:<fpage>1893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9836640</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9836640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>D'Uva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lauriola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Carolis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pacilli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D'Anello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Beta-catenin/HuR post-transcriptional machinery governs cancer stem cell features in response to hypoxia</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e80742</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0080742">10.1371/journal.pone.0080742</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260469</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolligs</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanash</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Activation of AXIN2 expression by beta-catenin-T cell factor. A feedback repressor pathway regulating Wnt signaling</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>21657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11940574</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11940574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tcherkezian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamarche-Vane</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<article-title>Current knowledge of the large RhoGAP family of proteins</article-title>. <source>Biol Cell</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17222083</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17222083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rehmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wittinghofer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<article-title>GEFs and GAPs: critical elements in the control of small G proteins</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>129</volume>:<fpage>865</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17540168</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17540168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>DerMardirossian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bokoch</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<article-title>GDIs: central regulatory molecules in Rho GTPase activation</article-title>. <source>Trends Cell Biol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>356</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15921909</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15921909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laukkanen</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kivela</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rissanen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rutanen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karkkainen</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leppanen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Adenovirus-mediated extracellular superoxide dismutase gene therapy reduces neointima formation in balloon-denuded rabbit aorta</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>1999</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2003</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">12370226</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12370226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borthwick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donne</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hampson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hampson</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The HPV16 E6 binding protein Tip-1 interacts with ARHGEF16, which activates Cdc42</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/sj.bjc.6606026">10.1038/sj.bjc.6606026</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21139582</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21139582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haura</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
<article-title>Src kinases as therapeutic targets for cancer</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Clin Oncol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrclinonc.2009.129">10.1038/nrclinonc.2009.129</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19787002</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19787002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boguski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<article-title>Proteins regulating Ras and its relatives</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>366</volume>:<fpage>643</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8259209</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8259209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pechlivanis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuhlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<article-title>Hydrophobic modifications of Ras proteins by isoprenoid groups and fatty acids&#x02014;More than just membrane anchoring</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>1764</volume>:<fpage>1914</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110180</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luttrell</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luttrell</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<article-title>Not so strange bedfellows: G-protein-coupled receptors and Src family kinases</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>7969</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15489914</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15489914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vigil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Der</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Aberrant overexpression of the Rgl2 Ral small GTPase-specific guanine nucleotide exchange factor promotes pancreatic cancer growth through Ral-dependent and Ral-independent mechanisms</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>285</volume>:<fpage>34729</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M110.116756">10.1074/jbc.M110.116756</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20801877</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20801877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vigil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cherfils</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossman</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Der</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Ras superfamily GEFs and GAPs: validated and tractable targets for cancer therapy?</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>842</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrc2960">10.1038/nrc2960</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21102635</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21102635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lazer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katzav</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<article-title>Guanine nucleotide exchange factors for RhoGTPases: good therapeutic targets for cancer therapy?</article-title><source>Cell Signal</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>969</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cellsig.2010.10.022">10.1016/j.cellsig.2010.10.022</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21044680</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21044680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cichowski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<article-title>NF1 tumor suppressor gene function: narrowing the GAP</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>604</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239415</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Theodorescu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sapinoso</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Conaway</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oxford</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hampton</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frierson</surname><given-names>HF</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Reduced expression of metastasis suppressor RhoGDI2 is associated with decreased survival for patients with bladder cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>3800</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15173088</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15173088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<article-title>Biphasic expression of RhoGDI2 in the progression of breast cancer and its negative relation with lymph node metastasis</article-title>. <source>Oncol Rep</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">17487395</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17487395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theodorescu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<article-title>RhoGDI signaling provides targets for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1252</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ejca.2010.02.025">10.1016/j.ejca.2010.02.025</ext-link></comment><object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20347589</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20347589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kogawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishihori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuribayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hagiwara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Anti-metastatic gene therapy utilizing subcutaneous inoculation of EC-SOD gene transduced autologous fibroblast suppressed lung metastasis of Meth-A cells and 3LL cells in mice</article-title>. <source>Gene Ther</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11313784</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11313784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smutney</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samulski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Secretion of extracellular superoxide dismutase from muscle transduced with recombinant adenovirus inhibits the growth of B16 melanomas in mice</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer Res</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>871</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14573788</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14573788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Youm</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Overexpression of extracellular superoxide dismutase (EC-SOD) in mouse skin plays a protective role in DMBA/TPA-induced tumor formation</article-title>. <source>Oncol Res</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16491951</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16491951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121441.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teoh</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oberley</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<article-title>Modulation of reactive oxygen species in pancreatic cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>7441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>
<object-id pub-id-type="pmid">18094428</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18094428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>